<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Goliahs head cut off with his own sword; in a combat betwixt little David, the young stripling, who stands in the power and strength of his God, and great Goliah the proud boaster, who stands in his own strength, glorifying in the arm of flesh, and contemning and despising little David, because of his youth. In a reply to a book, set forth by an un-named author, under pretence of an answer to thirty six queries, propounded by James Parnell, whom he in scorn calls, the young Quaker. And also an answer to severall counter-queries, propounded by the same unnamed authour, whom I understand to be one Thomas Draton, a teacher of the world, at Abbey Rippon, in Huntingtonshire, ... and also he that takes his part, who writes himself W.P. who knowes not the power of God, and therefore glories in the length of time, and the multitude of years. ... / Given forth from the spirit of the Lord in the behalf of Israel against the armies of the aliens, who muster up themselves against the Lord, and his authority: by a friend to the common-wealth of Israel, who is known to the world, by the name James Parnel. Who is a sufferer in outward bonds, for the testimony of the everlasting truth, in Colchester Castle. 1655.</title>
            <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E861_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203310</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863296</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115488</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91468)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115488)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E861[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Goliahs head cut off with his own sword; in a combat betwixt little David, the young stripling, who stands in the power and strength of his God, and great Goliah the proud boaster, who stands in his own strength, glorifying in the arm of flesh, and contemning and despising little David, because of his youth. In a reply to a book, set forth by an un-named author, under pretence of an answer to thirty six queries, propounded by James Parnell, whom he in scorn calls, the young Quaker. And also an answer to severall counter-queries, propounded by the same unnamed authour, whom I understand to be one Thomas Draton, a teacher of the world, at Abbey Rippon, in Huntingtonshire, ... and also he that takes his part, who writes himself W.P. who knowes not the power of God, and therefore glories in the length of time, and the multitude of years. ... / Given forth from the spirit of the Lord in the behalf of Israel against the armies of the aliens, who muster up themselves against the Lord, and his authority: by a friend to the common-wealth of Israel, who is known to the world, by the name James Parnel. Who is a sufferer in outward bonds, for the testimony of the everlasting truth, in Colchester Castle. 1655.</title>
                  <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46, 41-85, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread-Eagle, at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Drayton, Thomas.  An answer according to truth, that trembles not, nor quakes, nor quayleth.</note>
                  <note>W.P. =  William Parker?.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouember. 27.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drayton, Thomas, d. 1658? --  Answer according to truth, that trembles not, nor quakes, nor quayleth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>W. P.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115488:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115488:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOLIAHS HEAD <hi>Cut off with his own Sword;</hi> In a Combat betwixt little <hi>David,</hi> The young Stripling, who ſtands in the power and ſtrength of his God, and great <hi>Goliah</hi> the proud Boaſter, who ſtands in his own ſtrength, glorifying in the arm of fleſh, and contemning and deſpiſing little <hi>David,</hi> becauſe of his youth.</p>
            <p>In a Reply to a Book, ſet forth by an un-named Author, under pretence of an Anſwer to thirty ſix Queries, propounded by <hi>James Parnell,</hi> whom he in ſcorn calls, the young Quaker. And alſo an Anſwer to ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Queries, propounded by the ſame unnamed Authour, whom I underſtand to be one <hi>Thomas Draton,</hi> A Teacher of the World, at <hi>Abbey Rippon,</hi> in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> wherein his folly and ignorance, is much layd open, and the pride and deceipt of his ſpirit much manifeſted; And alſo he that takes his part, who writes himſelf <hi>W. P.</hi> who knowes not the power of God, and therefore glories in the Length of time, and the multitude of years. But <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was a wiſer man then great <hi>Goliah,</hi> ſaid, that the honourable age is not that which is of long time, neither that which is meaſured by the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of years; but wiſdom is the gray hair: and an undefiled life is old Age. And therefore let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdom, nor the ſtrong man glory in his ſtrength, for it is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>Given forth from the ſpirit of the Lord in the behalf of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Aliens, who muſter up themſelves againſt the Lord, and his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: by a friend to the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who is known to the World, by the name <hi>James Parnel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who is a ſufferer in outward bonds, for the teſtimony of the everlaſting truth, in <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Caſtle. 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle,</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115488:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115488:2"/>
            <head>The Title of the aforeſaid Book.</head>
            <head type="sub">An Anſwer according to truth, that trembles not, nor quakes, nor quaileth; given to thirty ſix Queries, propounded by <hi>James Parnell</hi> (commonly called the young Quaker) to an ancient Country Miniſter: with ſome Counter-Queries by the ſaid Minister, unto the ſaid young Quack and his fellows.</head>
            <p>HEre thou mayſt be aſhamed to ſtile thy ſelfe an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Miniſter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reply. Heb.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Job</hi> 4.14 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.10.</note> who manifeſts ſuch an <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> ſpirit, who with reproachfull words, makes a ſcoffe at the power of truth, which the Miniſters of God in all ages witneſſed, which made them to quake and tremble: And though the truth neither quake, nor quaileth, yet all that owned the truth, owned and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed quaking and trembling: which truth thou mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts thy ſelfe but a profeſſor of, and a ſtranger to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115488:3"/>power, and a deſpiſer thereof: and therefore out from among the Miniſters of Chriſt thou art raiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.3.</note> And thy Anſwer is not according to truth, but a Lie, as ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be made to appear hereafter, by him whom thou calls the young Quack, and it ſeems fear ſurpriſeth the heart of the Hypocrite,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P: F.</hi> 22.14, 15. <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
               </note> ſo that thou art aſhamed to own thy work with thy name;</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayſt, Courteous Reader, we are forced, notwithſtanding ſo many Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlets extant againſt the people called Quakers, to give anſwer to thirty ſix Queries of <hi>James Parnells,</hi> the young Quaker. Although thou haſt boaſted thy ſelfe an ancient Miniſter,<note place="margin">Rep.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns me as a young Boy, yet here it appears, that thou art glad of others to help thee to anſwer my Queries, as theſe words before mentioned doth teſtifie. And yet it is but a Pamphlet, as thou and thy helpers do confeſs, that thoſe many are, that are extant againſt the people called Quakers. And then thou run on in way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and ſcorn againſt me, becauſe of my youth; but the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> anſwereth you, That a poor and wiſe Child, is better then an old fooliſh King, who will no more be admoniſhed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> And therefore, when you think of your age, conſider alſo your folly, and let that ſtop your mouthes, from profeſſing your ſelves Ancients, who manifeſts ſuch a Light ſcornful ſpirit, and hates to be reformed.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayſt thou doubteſt not,<note place="margin">Prieſt.</note> but his Queries are the dictates of others, deceiving, and being deceived, which they yet put under the Boyes name, for the Credit of their cauſe.</p>
            <p>Here alſo without doubt,<note place="margin">Rep.</note> thy unbelieving heart is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, who without ground, meaſureſt others, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thine own heart, who becauſe thou makeſt uſe of the dictates of others, as here doth plainly appear: therefore cenſureſt others, which doth not adde credit to thy cauſe, becauſe thou boaſts of thy age.</p>
            <p>But according as thou believes,<note place="margin">Prieſt.</note> ſo be it to thee: yet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115488:3"/>nevertheleſs, thou ſhalt finde that the truth I ſhall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain againſt thee, who with thy unbelieving heart, art deceiving and being deceived, and then thou runs on in the pride of thy ſpirit, accuſing of me, to be ignorant of the truth of God, becauſe as thou ſayſt,<note place="margin">Prieſt.</note> of the falſe word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Queries.</p>
            <p>But with ſhame might thou ſpeak it;<note place="margin">Rep.</note> for openly haſt thou manifeſted to the underſtanding Reader, thy ſelfe to be a meer ſtranger, both to God and his truth alſo, who would limit the truth of God, to a humane art, which many of the Children of God had not;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13.</note> and therefore the power of God was the more manifeſted. And when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> was brought before the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, to wit, (the chief Prieſts and the Rulers) and they wondered at them, becauſe they perceived they was unlearned men; and thus with thy wiſdom, and thy great learning, thou art ſhut out of the truth in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall; but by this I do not own thy accuſation to be truth againſt me; for I have a Copy of the Queries of my own hand writing, which was the originall of thoſe that was ſent to thee, which will bear teſtimony againſt thee, to be a falſe accuſer, and how thou thy ſelfe haſt wronged them, and miſworded them, becauſe they was in the croſſe unto thy wiſdom. And to maintain this, thou bringeſt a ſtory in <hi>Eraſmus:</hi> nevertheleſs, the ſtory which thou bringeſt, doth not at all touch me, but may fitly be returned into thy new boſom, where it ſhall lie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then thou and thy Agent beſeeches the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to read without partiality; which if he do, he will judge no otherwiſe of you, then as I have declared, but will ſee how you have uttered forth your folly, and foamed out your ſhame, in going about to contradict the truth. And at the end of this your Epiſtle to the Reader, I finde <hi>W. P.</hi> which I judge to be one of thy Agents, to this your ſhamefull work, to which thou darſt not own thy name.</p>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115488:4"/>
               <head>My firſt Querie.</head>
               <p>Where,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Qu: P: An.</note> and how, and by, what waſt thou called to the Miniſtry which thou profeſſeſt? And in thy anſwer to this Querie, thou goeſt about to plead many excuſes, whereby to fly the anſwering of my Queries, ſaying it is eaſier for him that is yet in darkneſſe to propound doubts and Queries, then for ſome of the Children of light to anſwer them, on a ſudaine, which to proove thou quotes <hi>Daniel:</hi> &amp; that our ſaviour (thou ſaiſt) himſelf refuſed to anſwer the Phariſes interogatories till they had firſt anſwered his, <hi>Math.</hi> 21.23, 24.: And, allbeit thou ſaiſt thou might put me off with <hi>Solomons</hi> words <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.4. Anſwer not a foole according to his folly, leaſt thou alſo be like unto him,</p>
               <p>I did not propound the Queries unto thee, as any doubts of mine,<note place="margin">Rep:</note> but that thou in thy Anſwer thereunto might either prove thy practice, by the Scriptures unto them that are in doubt thereof, or unto them mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thy ſelfe to be a deceiver: which laſt thou haſt plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done to the leaſt Child of light, and therefore it doth not follow that I am in darkneſſe, or that thou art a Child of light. Neither did thou ſuddainely anſwer the Queries, though they concerned thy own condition, and therefore this place in <hi>Daniel,</hi> doth not at all ſtand for thee, for it was for <hi>Daniel</hi> to tell and interprete <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezers</hi> dreame, which was a hard thing for any to tell unleſſe it was immediately revealed to them by Gods ſpirit, as it was to <hi>Daniel;</hi> but all the Magitians and learned men, could not find it out by their arts, but moſt of theſe Queries unto thee was concerning thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition and practice, and herein thou manifeſts thy ſelfe to be in darkneſſe, who thus wreſts the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of its place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.11.</note> for thy own ends: and alſo <hi>Daniel</hi> was a man that feared the Lord, and trembled at his power, which now thou denies and ſcoffes at, and yet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115488:4"/>art not aſhamed, to take <hi>Daniels</hi> words for a refuge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light: And as for that Scripture in <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.23, 24. it ſhall be returned into thine own boſom, for it is thee, and ſuch as thee who are ſet up by the will of man, and authorized by the authority of man, who joyne with the Phariſes, and Scribes of theſe times, and combine together with the earthly powers to call us to Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by what authority we goe abroade preaching the truth from place to place, and crying againſt deceivers, &amp; where we had our commiſſion, becauſe we receive it not from man as you doe, but do witneſſe the ſame power &amp; authority as the Miniſters of God did in all ages, &amp; the ſame commiſſion: for they received not their commiſſion froo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, but was immediatly called &amp; immediately fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſent forth into the worke of the Miniſtry free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give as freely they had received, and was perſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them that was ſet up by the will of man; which alſo we do witneſſe, and therefore the Scripture afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, belongs unto thy generation who was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perſecuters, and if by propounding Queries thou judgeſt me to be in darkneſſe, then much more thou judgeſt and condemns thy ſelfe: for, for my 36. Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thou haſt propounded me 100; and here alſo thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts me a fool, as by the Scripture which thou quotes in <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.4. and therein manifeſts thy ſelfe ſo much the greater foole, in propounding ſo many Queries to mee, whom thou accounts a fool: and thus the pride of thy heart hath deceived thee.</p>
               <p>And whereas thou ſaiſt thou waſt inwardly called to the Miniſtry, by the motion and gifts of Gods Spirit,<note place="margin">P. An:</note> long before I was borne, which thou ſaiſt hath beene Gods ordinary way, which to prove, thou quotes <hi>Job.</hi> 32.8.2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.14. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.7.15. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch.</hi> 3.8.</p>
               <p>Though it hath beene, and is Gods ordinary way by his own power and Spirit,<note place="margin">Rep:</note> to call and fit his own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, for his own worke, as thoſe Scriptures afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned doth prove, which we alſo do witneſſe and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115488:5"/>do come no other way, yet theſe Scriptures do not at all prove where and how and by what, thou waſt called and <hi>Iahaziell,</hi> and <hi>Amos,</hi> and <hi>Micha,</hi> which thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures aforeſaid beares Teſtimony of, to be thus called, was men that ſpoake the word of the Lord freely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin and tranſgreſſion, and falſe-Prophets and hirelings, and their lives, ſealed their Teſtam ony: and theſe Scriptures alſo beares Teſtimony, how and where they was called, from their outward callings to ſpeake the word of the Lord, and ſo from thoſe Scriptures thou art ſhut &amp; haſt nought to do to take them into thy mouth forthey do not prove that thou waſt thus called from thy labour, for thou waſt brought up all thy daies in idleneſſe, and at an Univerſity (as you call it) to learne Arts and Sciences without which thoſe was called and fitted; and for any other Call than as the common na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Miniſters are called (who deny both immediate Revelation, and Inſpiration) thou haſt brought no proofe that will ſtand for thee, but onely thy own bare words, wherein thy life and practice will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee, for it is one with the Nationall preiſts and thou art maintained and upheld by the ſame power as the nationall Teachers are, neither doſt goe from place to place, reproving ſin in the Gate as <hi>Amos</hi> and <hi>Micha</hi> did, who was thus called, neither doſt ſpeake freely as they did, and therefore art a falſe Prophet, who ſaith the Lord ſaith, when he never ſpoke to thee, but run, and the Lord never ſent thee; and therefore thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits not the people at all, as is manifeſt by the fruits of thy Miniſtry, and thus thou waſt a deceiver before I was borne, and the Lord hath Raiſed me up to tell thee of it.</p>
               <p>Whether is thy Call &amp; meanes which thou profeſſeth mediate or immediate.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſaiſt, it was both: for ſaiſt thou beſides the immediate aforeſaid, thou waſt ordained a Miniſter by the Superiours, and Governours of the Church, as the Elders and Paſtors of the Churches
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115488:5"/>were formerly by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Act.</hi> 14.23. but thou ſaiſt thou doubteſt whether <hi>James Parnell</hi> well was called either way to be teacher; if ſo let him prove it by an infallible Teſtimony.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that have an inward call to the Miniſtry do not ſtay for an outward call by man,<note place="margin">Rep.</note> but goe forth in bedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the word of the Lord: whoſoever was called to the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, it was immediately, and not mediately; but thine mediately by the will of man, and not immediately as before is proved, and alſo out of thy own mouth is made manifeſt. For thou ſaiſt thou doubteſt whether I was called either way, but if thou was called and guided by the Spirit of the Lord, thou would'ſt know, without doubts, whether I was ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yea or nay: for the true Miniſters was Epiſtles writ in one another hearts, and they alſo know the falſe Prophets, and the falſe Apoſtles, and the falſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and declared againſt them as I do againſt thee, and without doubt I doe know thee to be a deceiver,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13.14. 15</note> 02 by an infallible Teſtimony, and thoſe that thou ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of, in <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. whom <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ordained Elders, they did not ordaine them Miniſters of the Goſpel, neither ſent them abroad to preach the Goſpel, 0 neither allowed them 100 or 200 pounds by the yeare, as thou haſt; but they choſe out thoſe that were ſtrong in the faith and ſet them to watch over the weake; but thoſe Churches, was gathered by the power and Spirit of God and was turned from darkneſſe to light, and was waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, clenſed, and ſanctified, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God; but out of your Church, caſt Drunkerds, and Swearers, and Liers, and Proud, and Covetous ones, and adulterous, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, and Quarrellers, and Fighters, and Scoffers,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> and Scorners, and Backbiters, and Envious ones, and Prophane and wanton ones, and the like, who are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waſhed nor ſanctified; and then ſee where will be the Church of England, and the Paſtors, Teachers, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115488:6"/>Elders,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rv.</hi> 3.</note> and all; then you that profeſs your ſelves to be the Church of Chriſt, will be found the ſynagogue of Satan, whoſe Miniſter thou art: and alſo <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> who ordained them Elders, was men indued with the holy Spirit of the Lord, and was immediately call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and choſen to the Miniſtry, and had a Spirit of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning to know who was fitted, for the Elder-ſhip; and all this was done without an Univerſity or ſerving ſeven yeares to learne Arts and Sciences, or taking De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, without which, you can do nothing: and alſo thoſe Superiors and Governours, that ordaine you tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and governours, have nothing but what they have gotten by art and ſtudy, and reading of others experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; but are ignorant of the power of God, neither knowes whether there be any Holy-Ghoſt, yea, or nay, but by the hearing of the eare: but ſcofs and ſcornes, and and perſecutes thoſe that now do witneſſe theſe things; and they themſelves was alſo firſt ordained by the will of man, and thus thou haſt but ſo much the more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted thy ſelfe to the world, in going about to prove thy ſelfe a called Miniſter by the Scripture, which doth altogether witneſſe againſt thee. And whereas thou would'ſt have me to prove my Call by an infallible Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, I tell thee without an infallible Teſtimony I do not goe, neither without an infallible Teſtamony doe I deſire to be received or owned, and to this the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Spirit of truth beares Teſtimony in all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of truth, and thou that haſt not an infallible Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony either with me or againſt mee, art ſtill in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and knowes not the truth then farre unfit to be a teacher to others.</p>
               <p>Whether thou art guided by the ſame infallible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that gave forth the Scripture.<note place="margin">3 <hi>Query</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer thou ſaiſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> that we our ſelves teach that all men are taught and guided by that Spirit at times: and ſecondly thou ſaiſt, thou praiſes God for it, thou art guided and aſſiſted by that Spirit which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115488:6"/>infallible: and thirdly thou ſaiſt thou doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any of thoſe that are called Quakers are alwaies guided by that Spirit.</p>
               <p>Here all that are guided by any meaſure of that Spirit may eaſily ſee thy lies and confuſion, for thy firſt is a lie,<note place="margin">Rep.</note> that any of us doe teach: that all men are taught and guided by that Spirit at times: for I deny that thou art, who art now taken with a lie in thy mouth, which all that underſtands our doctrine will witneſſe againſt, and ſecondly that thou art guided by an infallible Spirit, is a lie againſt the Holy-Ghoſt, for no lie comes from that Spirit. And againe thou belies the Spirit of truth to ſay thou art guided by it, and yet cannot give an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Teſtimony, whether thoſe thou calls Quakers are guided by an infallible Spirit, yea or nay, but art in thy doubts;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44.</note> but that Spirit is without doubts which now judgeth thee to be a lier, and thy God thou praiſes to be the Devill, the Father of lies, who muſt both be tormented together.</p>
               <p>Whether they that are guided by that Spirit need ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy how or what to ſay.<note place="margin">4 <hi>Qu.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer thou ſaiſt,<note place="margin">P. An:</note> 
                  <hi>Timothy</hi> had that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in a greater meaſure then <hi>James Parnell;</hi> yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith thus unto him as in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 14, 15, 16. And thou ſaiſt, if the Apoſtles had beene put to it to preach upon a ſhort Text or Theme, Methodically, as by long pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the Church is expected from you, they muſt oft times have ſtudied for it, as thou conceiveſt; though if you were left at large, to ſpeake as the Spirit of God mo es you, and giveth matter in, thou hopes ſome of you by Gods aſſiſtance, ſhould ſpeake as togood or better purpoſe then any whonow pretend to the ſpiritsactings.</p>
               <p>Here thou haſt ſufficiently manifeſted thy ſpirit,<note place="margin">Rep:</note> and thy ignorance of the ſpirit of God, to any who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the things of the ſpirit of God: and all theſe Scriptures which thou haſt brought concerning <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> doth not at all prove, that he that is guided by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115488:7"/>ſpirit of God, need ſtudy how or what to preach. But <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted <hi>Timothy</hi> to the gift that was in him, which was given him by, or for propheſie; for in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſhould ſave himſelf, and thoſe that heard him, which you never do, by the fruit of your ſtudy, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroyes them; witneſs the fruits of your Miniſtry, this many years in this Nation, who have wrought no better Reformation amongſt your hearers; and alſo this Scripture doth not at all prove, that <hi>Paul</hi> bid <hi>Timothy</hi> ſtudy old Authours, and heatheniſh Commentators, as you do: neither to ſtudy Arts and Sciences, as you do, who with your Philoſophy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</note> and vain deceipt, do ſpoile the people; for thou haſt manifeſted thy ſelfe to be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant of the ſpirit of God, who by thy own conceivings, judgeſt the ſpirit of God to be unſufficient to inſtruct and teach the Apoſtles what to ſpeak at all times, without ſtudy: when as Chriſt himſelfe exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, to take no thought what to ſpeak; for it ſhould be given them in the very ſame houre;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.19, 20.</note> for ſaith he, It is not you that ſpeaks, but the ſpirit of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſpeaketh in you, (which ſpirit ſpeaketh not without method) which ſpirit you Teachers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are great ſtrangers to, who think that the ſpirit of God can be limited to a Text, or a Theme; as thou confeſſeſt you are; but thou lier, where is now thy infallible ſpirit, who thus ſpeakeſt thy own conceivings, and therefore be aſhamed hence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to pretend to an infa lible ſpirit, who haſt here ſo openly manifeſied thy ignorance of it, and its movings, ſo that if thou waſt left at large to ſpeak from that ſpirit in thee, &amp; was ſhut out of thy Liberary &amp; from any Text or Writing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.10.</note> thou wouldſt plainly manifeſt thy ſelf, to be one of the dumb Dogs that could not bark, which <hi>I ſaiah</hi> from the ſpirit of the Lord declared againſt, without ſtudy: for I do believe, that if thou and the reſt of the natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Teachers, whom thou confeſſeſt, are tyed to a text or Theme, could tell how to pleafe the people, and get
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115488:7"/>gain without ſtudying or ſpeaking from a Text, you would for the credit of your cauſe, (as thou ſayſt): for I know nothing that ties you to it, but your own cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ends, to make a gain of theſe Scriptures, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ignorant with feigned words,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3.</note> whom <hi>Peter</hi> without ſtudy foretold of; and therefore thou Hypocrite, pretend no more to an infallible ſpirit, but with the reſt of thy Brethren, confeſs thou art void of it, as many of them have done; for in ſuch pretences thou art but the greater deceiver, and thy folly doth the more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
               <p>Whether is it as lawfull now for Tradeſmen,<note place="margin">5. <hi>Query.</hi>
                  </note> Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, or Plowmen, to preach if they be led by the ſpirit of God, as thoſe that ſpake forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer thou ſayſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſw.</note> if this was wholly grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>James Parnell</hi> cannot claim any intereſt therein, as thou conceiveſt; for, thou ſayſt, he is neither Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Plowman, or Shepheard, nor will take any courſe to maintain himſelf by his labour, for he hath been try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>But herein <hi>James Parnell</hi> can plainly tell thee,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> thou art a Lyer; for he followed a Trade with his Father, untill the Lord by his ſpirit called him from it, into his own work, &amp; ſo I obeyed the word of the Lord, and left my Father with his Trade,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37, 38.</note> as <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> did their Father in the Ship; <hi>for he that will not forſake Father and Mother, Lands and Livings, Wife and Children, and all for Chriſts ſake, is not worthy of him;</hi> in which work, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou nor any other can tax me for idleneſs; but I believe my labour and diligence in the ſame is more offenſive to you deceivers, then if I had been Idle. But he that would call me from this work that I am ſet about, into the work of man, I ſhould anſwer him, God muſt be ſerved before man; for if it had not been the will of God, to call me forth into his work, I ſhould ſtall have ſerved my earthly Father, ſooner then any other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115488:8"/>man, notwithſtanding the evill thoughts and conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſuch like as thee, who art given up to believe lies, and tell lies; but where is now thy infallible ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who ſpeakeſt by thy own conceivings, and thus the thoughts of thy heart deceives thee; and as for my maintenance, I need not a Law, to compel it as thou doſt, neither am chargeable to the World, as thou art, who by a Law of man, takeſt nigh 300. <abbr>l</abbr> by the yeare of them: therefore in this thou might have laid thy hand upon thy mouth, for thou and hundreds more of thy Brethren, never followed any honeſt Calling, whereby to get an honeſt livelihood, without being chargeable to the World, but was from your youths brought up at <hi>Babylons</hi> Schools, learning her wich-craft and ſorcery, thereby to deceive the Nations, and through covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with feigned words, make marchandize of them, which you nowſpare not.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly thou grants,<note place="margin">P. Anſw.</note> that if men be made of God ſpirituall, whether Shepheards or Plowmen firſt, they may teach; But thirdly, thou ſayſt, every man that hath the ſpirit in ſome meaſure, doth not attain to that height, growth, and degree, that they did, who gave forth the Scriptures, and therefore may not as lawfully, nor as infallibly teach as they did; and thou ſayſt, nor can thou diſcern clearly, that the beſt amongſt them called Quakers, have yet reached that degree or diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the ſpirit; and after much diſſembling ſpeeches, thou manifeſts thy light and frothy ſpirit, ſtill deſpiſing me, becauſe of my youth, but thy words are not worth mentioning.</p>
               <p>And thu swhen thou opens thy mouth,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> concerning the Spirit, thou manifeſts thy folly, and ignorance of the ſpirit, ſo that a Babe may comprehend thee, and tell thee of thy folly, and when thou thinkeſt of thy beard or age, (as thou ſayſt) confuſion of face may cover thee; for though every one, that hath the ſpirit in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, doth not attain to that height, grouth and degree,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115488:8"/>that they did who gave forth the Scripture: yet it doth not follow, that none doth attain to that grouth, height, and degree; and they that have attained to the ſame ſpirit in a meaſure, and by the ſame ſpirit are moved and called forth, may as lawfully, and as infallibly teach as they did, (in their meaſures) for the ſame ſpirit is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible in the leaſt meaſure, and its call is lawful; and thus thou ſheweſt, thou was never called, nor led by it, who art ſo ignorant of it; and as here alſo doth further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, in that thou confeſſeſt, thou diſcerneſt not the people called Quakers; and therefore art blind, and from thee the ſecrets of God are hid; and it doth not follow, that they are ever the leſs ſpiritual, but rather more, (becauſe thou canſt not diſcern them) who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends thy ſelfe a ſpiritual man; and thus they are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to that degree, they can diſcern thee to be a blind guide, and deceiver of the World; and therefore is thy ſpirit the more againſt them, for all thy flattering and diſſembling ſpeeches from thy hypocritical heart, who bends thy Tongue like a Bow againſt them, uttering forth lies in hypocriſie, and with thy ſconrful ſpirit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheſt me with lies; but it was thy Generation that quaked for fear of the downfall of their Kingdom; and therefore perſecuted me, and impriſoned me: yet their fear did not overtake me; for I was made as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſuffer, as they was to inflict, as knowing it was for his cauſe, who will make you all to quake and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who lift up your heels againſt him; and as thou compares <hi>Cambridg</hi> to <hi>Jericho,</hi> ſo the curſe of <hi>Jericho</hi> ſhal come upon it, for its whordom and ſorceries, and ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neckedneſs againſt the Lord and his anointed; and though thou thus ſcorneſt me, and deſpiſeſt me, becauſe of my youth, yet it is becauſe thou knoweſt not the Scripture, nor the power of God.</p>
               <p>Whether any are the Miniſters or Meſſengers of Chriſt, but thoſe that are guided by his ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Query</hi> 6.</note> and abide in his Doctrine, as the holy men of God was in Scripture,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115488:9"/>and whether the wind doth not now blow where it liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer to the firſt part,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> thou grants, that none are the true Miniſters, &amp; Meſſengers of Chriſt, but thoſe that are in ſome meaſure guided by his ſpirit, and abide in his Doctrine. But ſecondly, thou ſayſt, men may think, that they have that ſpirit, and yet be led by the lying ſpirit, as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> who ſmote <hi>Michajah,</hi> was, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.24.</p>
               <p>Herein thou markeſt out thy ſelfe for a deceiver, who pretends to the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> and it is the lying ſpirit, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proved, and ſo art ſhut out from the Miniſters and Meſſengers of Chriſt, who art not guided by his ſpirit, and therefore abides not in his Doctrine, as is before proved by thy ignorance of the true ſpirit: and therefore thou, and ſuch falſe Prophets as thou, thus ſmites at, and perſecutes us that are called Quakers, becauſe the Lord is pleaſed to beſtow his ſpirit upon us, whereby we are able to declare your deceipt, and manifeſt your lying ſpirits, who have profeſſed your ſelves, the Miniſters of Chriſt, yet ſtrangers to his ſpirit, and oppoſers of his truth, like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> who are men of corrupt mindes, and Reprobates concerning the faith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.</p>
               <p>And to the ſecond part of the Query thou ſayſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ:</note> that the wind doth blow where it liſteth, if it be not ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; yet are there many falſe windes, which blow like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from a deceiptful ſpirit, which to prove, thou quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. that we henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro with every winde of Doctrine; and ſayſt, Minde this <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I do minde, and ſtill ſees how thou markeſt out thy ſelfe with thy deceiptfull ſpirit;<note place="margin">Rep.</note> for if the winde do blowe where it liſteth, which thou acknowledgeſt: then what is that in you profeſſed Miniſters, which goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſtop it with gainſaying and perſecution, and would limit the ſpirit of God unto a Text or Theme,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115488:9"/>from which you with your deceitful ſpirits do raiſe, uſes points, tryalls and motives, &amp;c. whereby many poore Creatures are toſſed to and fro, and carried about with your airy ſpirits, with the ſlight and cunning craftineſs of your brains, whereby you ſtudy to deceive, as thou mayſt read in the latter end of the verſe, which thou haſt quoted, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14. which here ſhall ſtand againſt thee, and ſo, many are the Children which are toſſed to and fro by you, although they have both beards and age, (as thou ſayſt) yea ſome are 30. ſome 40, ſome 50, ſome 60, yea 80. and never yet come to the knowledge of the truth: and thus with feigned words, through covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you make Marchandize of the people, beguiling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſouls; but think not, that all you falſe Prophets, with the beaſt that upholds you, can ſtop or quench this ſpirit, which now bloweth where it liſteth; for with all the ſlight and craftineſs that you can uſe, you ſhall be made to fall before it, and the fruits of your labours ſhall be given you.</p>
               <p>Whether thou wilt own immediate Revelation now,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Query</hi> 7.</note> yea or nay?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer, thou ſayſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> the Apoſtle teacheth you to pray, for the ſpirit of wiſdom and Revelation in the acknowledgement of God: which to prove, thou quotes <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17. but ſayſt, there are many falſe lights and deluſions of Sathan, who too often transforms him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as an Angel of Light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. which thou ſayſt, are entertained by unwary men, for the Illuminations and Revelations of Gods ſpirit, as appears in <hi>Zedekiah</hi> aforeſaid; which to prove, thou quotes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.6. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>Here again, thou haſt marked out thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> and alſo belies the Apoſtle; for that Scripture in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17. onely makes mention how the Apoſtle prayed, for the <hi>Epheſians</hi> that believed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but it doth not at all prove, that the Apoſtle taught you that are of the world to pray; for the prayers of the wicked are abhominable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 15, 8.</note> and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would not teach ſuch to pray; and though in thy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115488:10"/>Anſwer, the ſubſtance of my Query is confeſſed, yet it doth not ſerve to prove that thou doſt witneſs it in thy ſelfe, or own it, where it is poſſeſſed; who would barre it from youth, and limit it to time and age, and ſo ſhewes thy ignorance of it, and that by the falſe lights and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Satan thou art deceived, who in thee rules as an Angel of Light: and ſo thou art one of thoſe unwary men who takes a lying ſpirit for an infallible ſpirit, as is both here and often before proved, who art found in <hi>Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> ſteps, and ſo art one of thoſe falſe Prophets, which the Prophet ſpeaks of, who ſaith, the Lord ſaith, when he never ſpoke to thee, as is before proved; and how long have you profeſſed Miniſters of this Nation, fed the people with expectations, and hopes that you would confirm what you have ſpoken unto them, which is not yet come to paſſe, neither likely; and thus you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them by your lying divinations, for your diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt gain; and therefore for this cauſe God hath given you up to ſtrong deluſions, that you ſhould believe a lie, that you all might be damned who believe not the truth now it is come unto you; but ſtill take pleaſure in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, as in thoſe Scriptures aforeſaid, which thou haſt quoted againſt thy ſelfe, and ſo they ſhall ſtand.</p>
               <p>What is the Goſpel which thou art a Miniſter of,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 8.</note> and whether thy Goſpel be free and without charge?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſayſt to the firſt part,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> that the Goſpel which thou preacheſt, is the ſame which Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, which thou ſayſt is ſummarily contained in theſe four verſes, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. wherein the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the grace of God to be their Teacher, to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, juſtly, and godlily in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World &amp;c. And to the ſecond part, thou ſayſt the Apoſtles Goſpel was not every way without charge; which to prove, thou quotes 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. and again thou ſayſt, Nor hath Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles, impoſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115488:10"/>it upon you, that the Goſpel ſhould be altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charge, unto them which have it taught: which to prove, thou quotes <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.27. And again thou ſayſt, nor is <hi>James Parnells</hi> Goſpel, be it right or wrong, without charge: If he do not take more then it is worth, if duly examined, it is well.</p>
               <p>Thy Spirit is much againſt <hi>James Parnell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rep.</note> as <hi>Zedekia's</hi> was againſt <hi>Michajah,</hi> yet here he can prove thee to be a lier, and not onely againſt him but of his Lord alſo: and therefore if thou belieſt the Lord, how much more the ſervant?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29.</note> for Chriſt Jeſus the Lambe of God was the Goſpel which the Apoſtles preached, which was free and not chargeable to any, though he was and is a burdenſom ſtone, to them that beleive not in him; yet not chargeable. And therefore thou blaſphemer, how dareſt thou to open thy mouth thus againſt the Lord and his anointed, who art ſtill in thy ungodlineſſe and worldly luſtes, who art pleading for the earth and art a ſtranger to the free grace of God, and therefore theſe verſes which thou haſt ſet downe, ſhall ſtand to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt thee, which thou ſaiſt containeth the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which thou preacheſt, but the Apoſtles Goſpel could not be contained in Paper &amp; Inke, for the heavens could not containe him, for he aſcended far above all Heavens that he might fill all things: and alſo of thy Goſpel thou makeſt a trade and a gaine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10</note> being many yeares at an Univerſity as thou caleſt it to learn to preach it: all which the Apoſtles did not, and ſo thou bringeſt another Goſpel, and ſo art not to be received but held as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, as thou art, who art not aſhamed to preſume to ſay, thy Goſpel is the ſame with the Apoſtle's, and thou doeſt here yeeld thy Goſpell to be chargeable, but this Scripture in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. doth not at all prove the Apoſtles to be chargeable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.9.</note> who ſaith he took wages of other Churches to do them ſervice, for it was but for his neceſſities, &amp; it was frely communicated to him &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no charge; but now you profeſſed Miniſters inſtead of robbing other Churches you rob &amp; oppreſſe the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115488:11"/>world, ruling over them by a law with force and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for the which you have no Scripture rule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4.</note> but amongſt the falſe ſhepherds. But whom do you ſpare, whether you do them ſervice or nay, if you can but get it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by faire meanes or foul? and therefore in this thou before many other might well have laid thy hand upon thy mouth. For whereas the Apoſtle there tooke ſome neceſſaries which was freely communicated to him by the Churches, thou takes nigh three hundered poundes by the yeare of the world, by a law of man, and none will ſpare who comes within thy bounds, whether thou doſt them ſervice or nay, and that Chriſt or any of his Apoſtles hath not impoſed it upon you that the Goſpel ſhould be altogether without charge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>J.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4</note> it is true, for they never intruſted you with it, though for ſucre ſake ye have run, though he never ſent you, and ſpeake a divination of your braine, but not from his mouth, and ſo profit not the people at all, but like ravening Wolves makes a prey upon them; but your end ſhall be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your workes, but they that are intruſted with the Miniſtry of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 17, 18.</note> have this charge impoſed upon them, As they have received freely, freely to give: the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſhewed the ſame example, whoſe care was to make the Goſpel free and without charge, and ſaid wo unto him, if he preached not the Goſpel, and therefore becauſe he would not make the Goſpel chargeable, he tooke neceſſaries of ſome, and ſpared others, and this was wiſdom (which you Earthwormes are void of) and thus he that is taught in the word may communicate to him that teacheth in all good things and yet without charge, he that can receive it, let him; the workman is worthy of his meate: and in that thou taxeſt <hi>James Parnell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.10.</note> he hath not beene chargeable to thee nor to thy generation, neither doth any of him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, although thou judgeſt him according to thy own corrupt heart, yet the anſwer of the juſt witneſſe in my conſcience ſhall be for me, before the righteous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115488:11"/>Judge of all hearts, when you Hirelings and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſhall wiſh the Mountaines to cover you, and the Rocks to fall upon you, and hide you from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence who will give you your reward in the lake that burneth, with the beaſt that now upholdes you in this your wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>Whether thou doſt hold up the firſt Prieſt-hood that tooke Tithes,<note place="margin">9. Query,</note> or the ſecond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prieſt-hood that tooke no Tithes &amp; which thou doſt deny, ſeeing thou takeſt Tithes?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſai'ſt,<note place="margin">P. An.</note> 
                  <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> whoſe Preiſt-hood was the firſt Prieſt-hood tooke Tithes and the Leviticall Prieſt-hood, which was the ſecond and not the firſt tooke Tithes alſo, ſo that thou faiſt there is no Prieſt-hood mentioned in the Scripture that tooke no Tithes: then thou Queries how thou or any other doth deny either of thoſe Preiſt-hoods by taking Tithes which to prove thou quotes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2, 3, 4.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, thou Serpent! although thou thus twines about to cover and ſhelter thy deceipt,<note place="margin">Rep.</note> under others wings it will not at all ſerve to prove, that thereby thou doſt not deny Jeſus Chriſt come in the fleſh, who is the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting high Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck</hi> which is the unchangeable Prieſt-hood, the end of the changeable, which tooke Tithes, and ſo, the end of Tithes, as is proved by that Scripture which thou haſt quoted, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. and chap. 8.1. wherein the Apoſtle ſpeaks how <hi>Abraham</hi> paid Tithes to <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> of the ſpoils which he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> got in the warr which was a free gift without either law or compulſion; neither did ſtand for a law or rule to the generations following un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the law was given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh, and the changeable Prieſtood eſtabliſhed: which I ſay was the firſt Prieſt-hood, to which Tithes was due, for it was ſo the command of God, that the Tithes ſhould be paid unto the changeable Prieſt-hood, and they was to have a ſtore-houſe, wherein the Tithes was to be put.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115488:12"/>And the Widdows and the Fatherleſſe and the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers was to come and be filled within their gates that there ſhould not be a begger in <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.28, 29.</note> which ſtatute is now rejected by you who now ſo gape for Tithes: for ye inſtead of doing this, do grind the faces of the poore, and oppreſſe the Widdows, the Fatherleſſe, and the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers if they doe come within your bounds, and, ſo makes beggers rather then otherwiſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.15.</note> ſo that if you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Tithes by this law, it will witneſſe againſt you, and alſo in ſo doing you deny Chriſt Jeſus come in the fleſh, who when he was offer'd up, was the everlaſting offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the everlaſting high Prieſt over the houſhold of God, and ſo the fulfilling and the end of the changeable who tooke Tithes by a command. And ſo, ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, the Prieſt-hood being changed there muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be a change of the law, and ſo the command was diſanulled and Tithes ended: for ſaith the Apoſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1. Now of the things that we have beene ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>7.12.</hi> Here thy <hi>66</hi> Qu. is Anſ.</note> this is the ſumme, we have ſuch an high Prieſt, that is ſet on the right hand of the throne, &amp;c. Now Tithes was one thing, and the Prieſt-hood was another thing and the law (by which they both was upheld) was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, of which the Apoſtle had beene ſpeaking of which he ſaith this is the ſumme, Chriſt Jeſus the high Prieſt that is ſet on the right hand of the Throne, and ſo the fulfilling and the end of theſe things before mentioned, of which Tithes is one: ſo by this new Covenant he hath made the firſt old;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13.</note> now that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayeth or waxeth old is ready to vaniſh away. Now marke then, which Prieſt-hood the Apoſtle here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts firſt, becauſe thou accuſeſt mee, that I know not which was the firſt and which was the laſt, but by this it is proved that you that now ſo gapes for Tithes under the profeſſion of the Goſpel, are razed out from <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> who once tooke Tithes, onely of the ſpoile which was taken in the war, which was a free gift unto him, (which now you have not) and alſo are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115488:12"/>raſed from the changeable Prieſt-hood which was the firſt to which Tithes was due, by a command for its time; and alſo do deny Chriſt come in the fleſh who is the end and fulfilling of thoſe things, which without command, for lucre ſake, you now uphold, and cry up; and ſo are found onely the Miniſters of Antichriſt, who oppoſe the true Chriſt, (where he is witneſſed and held forth) yet under a profeſſion of his name: therefore he will profeſſe unto you workers of iniquity, that he knows you not, when you knock &amp; are not able to enter.</p>
               <p>Where is thy Rule in the Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Query</hi> 8.</note> from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel to take Tithes?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> Thou much endeavours to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and cover thy ſelfe by the Scripture, but it will not hide thee, nor ſtand for thee; to prove that the Miniſters of the Goſpel ever took Tithes, or that unto them Tithes belonged, as any who reads thy Anſwer with underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, may ſee &amp; alſo ſee thy ſhuffings, who runs into the old Covenant to maintain Tithes due to the Miniſters of the new Covenant, which is the end of the old, as in my laſt Reply is plainly proved; and thou out of both to be ſhut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; therefore thou ſayſt, it is ſufficient for thee, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters of the Goſpel, that there is no Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in the Goſpel againſt the taking of Tithes, which thou ſayſt, we muſt produce ere we can make the thing unlawfull.</p>
               <p>Now all people may conſider, how they have been blinded and deceived by you profeſſed Miniſters of the Goſpel in this Nation, who upon ſuch ſlender grounds as theſe, have and do take the tenth of the increaſe of the fruits of the peoples labours, who many of them, themſelves do rent and hire what they have, whereby you have and do live at eaſe, in pride, idleneſs, and fulneſs, ſporting in the day time, and living in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and wantonneſs upon the earth, contrary to any Rule or Example in the Scripture, from the Miniſters of the Goſpel; and therefore this your ground and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115488:13"/>foundation which thou haſt here laid beſides the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to uphold Tithes contrary to the Scripture, will not ſtand, and therefore your building muſt fall; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there were no Command in the Goſpel againſt the taking of Tithes: yet it doth not prove, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel are to take Tithes, being it was never allotted them; but that by the Goſpel, Tithes are diſannulled, and the Prieſthood changed, and the Law by which they both was eſtabliſhed; is fulfilled and done away, is clear by the Scripture; and therefore unlawful now for any to practiſe without a Command from God, as before is proved in my laſt Reply, ând thou to be a lier, who ſaith, I could not prove it by clear Scripture, that Chriſt or his Apoſtles hath taken away that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; and therefore that Scripture which thou haſt quoted in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. ſhall ſtand and witneſs againſt thee; for when Chriſt ſpoke, that was before he was offered up, and then the Law of Tithes was not yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and therefore not diſanulled; and therefore ſtrictly to be obſerved, untill Chriſt the everlaſting ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was offered up; and then the Apoſtles ſaid, the Prieſthood being changed, there muſt of neceſſity be a change of the Law, and ſo Tithes ended, as before is proved; and therefore not for the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, to take them as theit maintenance; and that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which thou haſt quoted in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. ſhall ſtand and witneſs againſt thee; for the whole Chapter doth not at all prove Tithes due to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as any who reads the Chapter with honeſty will witneſs; for it doth not at all mention Tithes, but only ſpeaks of the Apoſtles power, that as they had planted Vineyards, ſo they might eat of the fruit thereof; and as they preached the Goſpel, ſo they might live of the Goſpel; and this the Apoſtle writ to thoſe whom he ſaid was the Seals of his Miniſtry; but where is the Seals of your Miniſtry?<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.19.</note> are they not the world who lie in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? where is the Vineyard that ye have been planting
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115488:13"/>this many years? is it not ſtill full of Briers and Thorns, and weeds, and wild Plants, which bring forth no fruit, but cumber the ground: but keep in your own Vineyards, and rob not others, and then you will not be ſuch Theeves as you are, but it will make you plant better, or elſe to fall to ſome other Trade; and the Apoſtles power was not of man, nor by man, being he was not ſet up by man; but yours is of man, and by a Law of man, by whom you are ſet up, and by whom you ſtand, as here in thy anſwer thou haſt confeſſed; and yet the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to uſe this power, and yet ſaid, neceſſity was laid upon him to preach the Goſpel; but what power do you refuſe, be it right or wrong? and if that earthly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould be taken from you, which you have, what would become of your Goſpel? nay ſome of you have ſaid, that Down with the maintenance, and down with the Miniſtry; and therefore for ever ſtop thy mouth, from taking the Apoſtles words, for a Cloak for thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, who himſelf caſt out ſuch from the Miniſtry, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and therefore thou knew, that none of theſe Scriptures would ſerve for thy ends; and therefore thou would ſhelter thy ſelfe under the powers of the earth, by whom thou art ſet up, whom thou ſayſt, did give to the Miniſters of the Goſpel in this Nation, and elſe where, and to their ſucceſſor for ever, the tenth of all their grounds, and cauſed them to be ſetled by a Law. And thou askeſt, If this was not a lawful and pious gift, and ſuitable to what was payd in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>This I do deny to be lawful, but altogether unlawful;<note place="margin">Reply. Thy 6th Query is anſwered in this Reply. <hi>2</hi> Pet. <hi>3.16.</hi>
                  </note> for that hath made ſo many pretended Miniſters as there are, who for greedineſs of the gain and pleaſure, have pretended to the things which you never had in you, neither know any thing of them, but by others Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which for your own ends, you have wreſted to your own deſtruction and others, and ſo through your Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and vain deceipt, have ſpoiled the people, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115488:14"/>by feigned words through covetouſneſs, have made Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of them, and ſo have deluded and led in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the people this many years, only for your own car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ends; and that this is ſuitable to what was payd in the old Teſtament, I alſo do deny (and if it was, what is that to you? that which was given in the old Teſtament is diſannulled by the new, and therefore no rule for you) and alſo that was given by the Lord to the Levites, who had no other Inheritance in the Land, and the Lord gave that which was his own, and he gave a ſtrict Command, that it ſhould be payd, which ſtood in force ſo long as the Prieſthood endured, as is proved by the Scriptures, which thou thy ſelfe haſt quoted which ſhall here ſtand againſt thy ſelfe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30, 31, 32. and <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.24. but the Lord did not give it ſince to the profeſſed Miniſters of <hi>England;</hi> but thou ſayſt, man gave it, and therefore gave that which was none of their own; for it is unjuſt for any Prince or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, to give away the labour or Inheritance of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects unto them that never laboured for it, and unto theſe who under pretence of the Goſpel do delude, and beguile the ſouls of his Subjects, for their diſhoneſt gain, as you profeſſed Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do; and therefore they whoſe eyes are opened,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.5.</note> do ſee you, and therefore accounts it a ſin unto God, to uphold you, or put into your mouthes, whom the Lord is againſt; and therefore you even prepare Warre againſt them, and it is neither pious nor lawful, for any Prince or Governour, to force any of his Subjects by a Law, contrary to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; and alſo the Inheritance of the Levites, was ſtated by a Law of God, and yours by a Law of Man, and they was ordained, and ſet up by God, but you by man, by whom you are upheld and maintained contrary to Scripture: ſo they come by the will of God, &amp; you by the will of man; &amp; they was maintained by the will of God, &amp; you by the will of man, &amp; they were of God (as all his true Miniſters are now,) and you are of man, (as all the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115488:14"/>falſe Prophets, and falſe Miniſters ever was,) ſo that there is much difference betwixt you and them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Intereſt, that they had in Tithes, and the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that you now claim: ſo that they that robbed them, robbed God, as in the Scripture which thou haſt quoted, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. which ſhall ſtand againſt thee; and if the ground of your intereſt was well ſearched, it would be found that you have it from the Pope and his upholders, whoſe ſupremacy your ſelves deny in words to blinde the World; but in practice you own it, and claim it: and again, if this which thou ſpeaks of, was given to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, then you that are hirelings, and the Miniſters of Antichriſt have no right nor title in it; and the Miniſters of the Goſpel, they alſo do deny it, whoſe care is to make the Goſpel free and without charge; and therefore cannot oppreſs any, neither will their Conſciences ſerve them to take the increaſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers labours, by Law or compulſion, and therefore it is moſt juſt, that the Labourer ſhould in peace, injoy the fruits of his labours, and ſuch idle drones as you (who neither labour for God, nor for the good of man, but are the deſtroyers both of body and ſoul) ſhould not eat according to the Apoſtles Rule, in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. and thus unto it you have no legall nor civil claim, (as thou calls it,) but your Birth-right is as a meſſe of Pottage: neither is your Claim and Title, as lawful as a Sonnes is to the Inheritance of his Father (as thou ſayſt;) but you climbe up another way &amp; ſo are Theeves &amp; Robbers, <hi>John</hi> 10.1.</p>
               <p>Whether ever the Miniſters of Chriſt had or ſtood in need of an outward Law,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 11.</note> to compel people to maintain them, as thou, and ſuch as thou now hath and doth.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou confeſſeſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſw.</note> that thoſe that are righteous or truly ſpirituall, needs no ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive Law to force them; for they are a Law unto themſelves; but thou ſayſt, that the greateſt part of the profeſſors in the viſible Church, alwayes were, and yet are earthly-minded, and neither do nor can, rightly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue ſpiritual and heavenly things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115488:15"/>
But in all thy pretended Anſwer, thou doſt not at all, reſolve the ſubſtance of my Query, but rather in thy ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in it, doſt yield thy ſelf out of the practiſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and by thy own confeſſion it is manifeſt, that neither you profeſſed Miniſters, nor your Auditors are righteous, nor truly ſpiritual, for you ſtand in need of a compulſive Law, to force people to maintain you, and the people ſtands in need of a compulſive Law to force them to maintain you, which thou confeſſeſt the righteous need not; but though you have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive Law, the righteous will not maintain you: and thus out of thy own mouth thou art judged, and the reſt of thy Brethren to be the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who profit not the people at all; and again, thy own confeſſion proves it, that the greateſt part of your Church is earthly minded, and no wonder while the Teachers themſelves are ſo; and thus your Church is the Synagogue of Sathan, which is built up of ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; and therefore bluſh and be aſhamed of your Miniſtry. Oh what have you been doing this many years! who have wrought no better Reformation: and herein you ſhew your Miniſtry to be earthly, who have no better ſeals then earthly minded profeſſors, who ſtand in need of a Law to compel them to maintain you; and this is as true a ſaying, as any thou haſt in thy Book that the greateſt part of the profeſſors in your Church are earthly minded; but, in that thou accuſeſt the Church in the Apoſtles dayes to be the ſame, thou art a lyer and a falſe accuſer, neither canſt bring any proofe in the Scripture, to maintain what thou ſayſt, but it will witneſs againſt thee;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4.33, 34, 35. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.1.8.</note> for the multitude that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, were of one heart, and one ſoul, ſo that they ſold their poſſeſſions, and laid it at the Apoſtles feet; and it was diſtributed to every one, according as they had need: the Miniſtry took ſuch place in them. And whereas there was two found that was earthly minded, yet there needed not a Law of man to compel them; and the Law of man alſo was againſt the Apoſtles, as it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115488:15"/>is againſt theſe now that walk in the ſame ſteps, yet they do not need a Law of man to force a maintenance for them, from worldly or earthly minded profeſſors, as the falſe Prophets and deceivers alwayes did, who was alwayes ſheltered and upheld by the will of man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could wink at their iniquity, and cry peace to them as thou here doſt, becauſe they put into thy mouth: therefore thou flatters them, and daubs them up, but it is with untempered morter. But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which Chriſt gave to his Miniſters, was,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22 22.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> Take no thought, but into whatſoever City or place they entered, they was to enquire who was worthy; and if they was not willingly received, they was to ſhake off the duſt of their feet, and ſo leave them; but is it not well known, that all your care is to take thought, where to get a fat living, inſtead of inquiring who is worthy; and there if you have but Authority from man, you will have it, whether they receive you, yea or nay: ſo with ſhame mighteſt thou bring any example from the Apoſtles, or the Church in their dayes, who were men that coveted no mans Silver nor Gold nor apparrell but had forſaked all for the Goſpels ſake, and many of the Church ſuffered the ſpoiling of their goods wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly by your fore-Fathers the cheife Prieſts and Scribes and Phariſes, who was their perſecutors, as you are now of them who the Goſpel do own,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 20.33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34.</note> (and your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors alſo) who as thou ſaiſt doth not rightly value ſpirituall things, ſuch as are holden forth by the true Miniſters and Meſſengers of God, (neither can) becauſe, by ſuch blind guides as thou art, they are kept in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and darkneſſe, leaſt their eies ſhould be opened and they come to ſee you, and decline from you, who was never tied to you by any command of God, and therefore you are glad to make uſe of a law of man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the practiſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: and as for the expreſſe proviſion, which the Lord made for his Miniſters and Meſſengers in the new Teſtament, I reply, When Chriſt gave them their Commiſſion, he ſaid alſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115488:16"/>in whatſoever houſe they entered they was to eate ſuch as was ſet before them, for ſaith he the workman is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his meate: and this is all the expreſſe proviſion that thou canſt find allotted to them in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this was without any law of man too; for there was no need of any, for if they did not willingly receive them, they was not to eate with them, but to ſhake of the duſt of their feete againſt them, and that was all the law they was to take againſt ſuch which was earthly minded, and regardleſſe of them: but this will not ſerve you becauſe your ſelves are earthly minded, and therefore will have it of every one, whether they receive you yea or nay, or elſe you have a law of man to take treble damage; and inſtead of eating ſuch as they will ſet before you, you will have the tenth part of what they have by compulſion, you are ſuch greedy devouring Woolvs: and what was before allotted to the Prieſts in the old Teſtament, is before ſufficiently proved to be nothing concerning you, who profeſſe your ſelves Miniſters of the New Teſtament, and as for thoſe Scriptures which thou quotes in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.5, 6. <hi>&amp;c:</hi> are alſo as nothing to my Query, but are before anſwered in my laſt reply, but yet theſe ſhall ſtand to witneſſe againſt thee to be a liar: for let any who reades theſe verſes, ſee if there the <hi>Iſralites</hi> did ſhew any earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindedneſſe, or ſtood in need of a law to compel them, after they knew the Kings mind, (as thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeſt them) and thus thou canſt find nothing either in the Old or New Teſtament that will cover thy deceipt but altogether witneſſe againſt thee, and therefore againe thou flees into thy old ſhelter which is the will of man, by which thou art ſet up and upheld, therefore a falſe Prophet, and a deceiver, who abides not in the doctrine of Chriſt, and it is no Pious nor Juſt act for them as I ſaid before, to take away the fruits of their ſubjects labours by a compulſive law to give unto ſuch Earth-wormes as thee, who cares not how you get it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115488:16"/>ſo you get it, as thy own mouth confeſſeſt, for thou ſaiſt it is a competent though not a liberall maintenance; and yet thou canſt take it and plead for it too, yea and of worldly minded people, which is altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Apoſtles practiſe, and ſo thou fullfills the wordes which before I have ſpoken of thee, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever denies you of Tithes do not unjuſtly detaine them, (as thou ſaiſt they do) being you have no right to them by any law or command from God, or example in the Scripture, as before is proved, but only claimes a Title by the unjuſt ſupremacy of the Pope, by which your fore-Fathers, the perſecuting Biſhops was upheld, and therefore we called Quakers do teach people them you to deny, which is not contrary to the practice of Chriſt or his Apoſtles (as thou accuſeſt us) for ſaith Chriſt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe-Prophets that appeare in ſheeps clothing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15.16.</note> but inwardly ravening Woolves; by their fruits they are knowne, and by which ſufficiently you are here marked our, and the Apoſtles bids from ſuch turne away as in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. and againe the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> forbids to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch as abides not in the doctrine of Chriſt, or to bid them God ſpeed 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.10. and here both Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſufficiently taught people to deny you, and here thou art proved a lier who thus falſely accuſeſt us called Quakers, in this to act contrary to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Chriſt or his Apoſtles, and ſo here thou and the reſt of the profeſſed Miniſters of this Nation, are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently manifeſt what you are; ſo that all men may ſee your folly and deceipt, but thoſe who are blind, and love to have it ſo, and ſo the Scripture is fulfilled upon you, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30.31.</p>
               <p>Whether ever the Miniſters of the Goſpel tooke any neceſſaries of the world,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Que.</hi>
                  </note> as thou and ſuch as thou doth all your Tithes and maintenance yea or nay?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſaiſt, yea they have,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> which to prove thou quotes, <hi>Ast.</hi> 28.1.9. where thou ſaiſt <hi>Paul</hi> tooke neceſſaries of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> yet this not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115488:17"/>ſerving thy turne, thou runs to old Hiſtories which thou calls <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> records, and ſaith they for 1500 yeares doe teſtify the ſame, but yet doubting of this, thou ſaiſt as thou ſaid before, it ſufficeth you that there is no law nor command of God, to the contrary; nor are exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples thou ſaiſt needfull for every thing; as to prove that Chriſt called any ſhooemaker or cobler to be a Prophet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reply.</note>But here againe thou haſt marked out thy ſelfe to be a falſe Prophet, who runs, and the Lord never ſent thee, and therefore thou teacheſt for Doctrine the traditions of men; for the which thou haſt no Scripture &amp; therefore runs to old ſtories, to which I am not to give any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, be they never ſo old, being they are not according to Scripture, (and therefore not Eccleſiaſticall) for the old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the thing doth not make it truth; though you haue long thereby deceived the ignorant. And as for that Scripture which thou quoteſt in <hi>Acts</hi> 28.1.9. then <hi>Paul</hi> was a Priſoner, and he and the Souldiers that kept him and the reſt of the people, was driven there by ſtorm upon the Sea, ſo that in that cauſe the <hi>Barbarians</hi> took pitty of them, and received them; but there was many beſides <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Centurion, to whom <hi>Paul</hi> was committed, was to take care of him, and alſo that which the Barbarians did was freely, and that which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bound them to, being they was in that ſtrait; which was done to many beſides <hi>Paul,</hi> who were heathen, ſo that this doth not at all ſtand for thee, who art in thy own Country, and yet takes all thy Tithes and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the World by compulſion: neither will this excuſe ſerve to ſhelter you Hirelings and deceivers, to ſay that there is no Law nor Command of God to the contrary; for it is falſe; for Chriſt commands his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters expreſly, freely to give, as freely they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and alſo charged them where they was not freely received,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Mich.</hi> 1.2.</note> to depart thence, ſhaking off the duſt of their feet, as before is proved, and alſo oppreſſion is the Law of God againſt, and to take the tenth, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115488:17"/>of the fruits of the peoples labours, is a ſore and great oppreſſion which the Land groans under, and therefore a ſin, and yet the gift doth ſo blinde your eyes, that you cannot ſee all this, but thinks, becauſe there is no Scripture for you, therefore none againſt you: and though there needs no example to prove any Shooma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker or Cobler to be a Prophet (as thou confeſſeſt) though in ſcorn,) for it is a thing that none doth, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the Scripture, being there is ſufficient proof, that he called other Tradeſmen; yet there is a need, that you might finde ſo much as a Scripture proof, or example, for your Tithes and maintenance, (who profeſs it to be your rule) being it is a great oppreſſion of the Land; and yet ſayſt thou, it doth ſuffice you, that there is no Law or Command to the contrary: therefore this ſhews your avaricious mindes, who are ſo willing to be blinde in this things; but it will not, neither doth ſo eaſily ſuffice thoſe that are oppreſſed by you, though you regard it not, according to the Prophet <hi>Ezekiels</hi> words, you ſeek for the fleece, and regard not the flock, but make a prey upon the ſheep: and ſo with this ſtop thy mouth, and own thy ſelfe amongſt the falſe Shepheards and Hirelings, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>John</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Whether ever they had a ſet maintenance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que:</hi> 13.</note> or ſo much a year for preaching, as 40.60.100. or 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> as thou, and ſuch as thou hath.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ. i</note> thou canſt not bring one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for thy Rule, to prove this your common practiſe, but flees to the Records, that thou ſayſt are to be found in ſeverall parts of Chriſtendom, (as thou calls it) where I do not intend to ſeek for them, to ſee whether theſe things be true or no, which thou ſpeakeſt of them; but as I ſaid before, will conclude them to be falſe in this thing, being the Scripture is altogether againſt it, ſo that thou canſt not finde one Scripture to juſtifie it; but ſayſt, if we ſay Where do you read of this in the Scripture; thou anſwers as far off again to the ſame purpoſe ſtill, without any Scripture proof, and therefore I ſhall leave it for any underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115488:18"/>Reader of thy Book to judge, and ſee how weak you are, if you had not a Law of man to uphold you, who have not one Scripture that will ſtrengthen the foundation of your Miniſtry, which is your mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: then how have you deluded the people to make them believe, that the Scripture is your Rule, when it is altogether againſt you, let the honeſt hearted judge.</p>
               <p>And whether ſuch be not the hirelings which cares not for the ſheep yea or nay;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 14.</note> And whether ſuch be not the greedy Doggs which the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> freely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt <hi>Iſay</hi> 56.11. and makes a prey upon the ſheep, which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> declared againſt, <hi>Ezek</hi> 34. and are the ravening Wolves which Jeſus Chriſt declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. and are ſuch as through covetuouſneſs, makes Merchandiſe of the people, which <hi>Peter</hi> a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt declared againſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. and ſuch as go after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for gifts and rewards, which <hi>Jude</hi> a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, cryed woe againſt, <hi>Jude</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> after many excuſes thou plainly confeſſeſt, thou canſt not juſtifie all of your Calling, and therefore thou wilt anſwer for thy ſelfe; and firſt thou ſayſt, thou art none of theſe Hirelings; for he is not an Hireling which takes the wages allotted to him for his work; for then thou doſt accuſe Kings &amp; Governours to be Hirelings, who takes Tribute and Cuſtom, yea and the Apoſtles and Chriſt himſelf, which to prove, thou quotes 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.8, and <hi>Luke</hi> 8.23. but thou confeſſeſt, that he is one, that ſets his heart upon the wages only, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights not in the work, but is weary of the ſame, and longs for the ſhadow or reſt, which to prove, thou quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Job</hi> 7.1.2, 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reply.</note>Here, thou impudent lyer, for all thy ſhuffelings and thy coverings, thou canſt not hide thy ſelfe, but out of thy own mouth ſhalt be judged, though thou here plainly denies thy Brethren, and thinks it enough to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for thy ſelfe, thy cauſe is ſo bad; for thy wages is not alotted by God, neither haſt thou any Scripture Rule to prove them, (as is before proved) and therefore
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115488:18"/>it follows, that thy heart is ſet upon thy hire; for which ſake thou undertakes that work which thou profeſſeſt, and it is for thy hires ſake, that thou art not weary of thy work, or elſe thou wouldſt not own that which is ſo contrary to the Scripture: ſo that thou canſt not bring one Scripture proof for this thy practice: and, that it is thy hire that thou delights in, is ſufficiently appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, by thy thus gaping for it, and ſeeking to defend it, though altogether contrary to Scripture: And as for the work thou and thy Brethren profeſſeth, you are as idle in it as you can, ſo that you can but hold up the Worlds cuſtom, and blind the people that ſtill you may rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them by your meanes, and thus it may plainely be ſeene, wherein is your delight, and ſo out of thy own mouth judge thee to be neither conſcionable nor faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who art not aſhamed thus to ſeeke to juſtifie thy ſelfe in thy deceipt, when as thy own mouth confeſſeth that it is not a liberall maintenance, and that thou canſt take it and plead for it: and therefore this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which thou quoteſt, in <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.2. ſhall ſtand and witneſſe againſt thee, who as a hireling agrees with the people for ſo much a yeare, and as a hireling lookes for thy wages at the yeares end, but of thy work there is no profit to any, and ſo with the ſhaddow thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveſt them for gaine which doth ſo blind thy eie, that thou thinkeſt all are like thee, though they take that which is freely adminiſtred to them for their temporall neceſſities; which is not agreeing with the people, for ſo much a yeare, and to take it by a law whether they will agree with you yea or nay; which weapons Chriſt or his Miniſters never made uſe of, and therefore thou lier how darſt thou to accuſe Chriſt or his Apoſtles to take wages for their worke? did Chriſt heale the ſick or the diſeaſed, and the lame, and the blind, or teach the people, for mony or wages? oh thou blaſphemer for ever ſtop thy mouth from nameing his holy name who doth ſo ſlander him: well maiſt thou accuſe and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115488:19"/>ſlander his Servants and Meſſengers, which ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently doſt it to him, who is our Lord and Maſter: but as for paying tribute,<note place="margin">3.</note> to Kings and Goverours in their places it is allowed of by Scripture, which thine is not, and they are ſet about temporall affaires and are the ordinance of God for that purpoſe, for to Governe and Protect the people in bodily peace and quietneſſe, which if they neglect, will be laid to their charge: but thou and thy brethren pretend to ſpirituall affaires, and therefore are to have your rule and example from Chriſt and his Miniſters who was ſet about ſpirituall affaires, the which thou canſt not but would creepe into any hole, to hide thy ſelfe and thy brethren from the light, but by it are you found out, and ſeene, to be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers who out of the doctrine of Chriſt are found, and therefore not to be owned nor received.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly thou ſayſt, thou art no ſuch greedy Dogge,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> whatſoever foul-mouthed Curs do bark to the contrary; for thou ſayſt, thou contents thy ſelfe with thy legall ſallary, which yet thou ſayſt is not contrary to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall, (wherein thou haſt already been proved a Lier ſufficiently.)</p>
               <p>Here thy foul mouth thou haſt opened wide, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reply.</note> a foul mouth'd Cur, who this Language firſt did ſpeak unto the falſe Prophets, in whoſe ſteps thou art found, and therefore unto thee the ſame Language belongeth, who ſeeks for thy gain from thy Quarters as they did; and what haſt thou elſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted but greedineſs of gain all along,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay.</hi> 56.</note> who rather then thou would yield thy error in it (though thou couldſt not produce one Scripture that would ſtand for it:) yet thou runneſt to old Hiſtories &amp; Records, thereby to maintain it, contrary to Scripture: therefore with ſhame &amp; confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of face might thou ſay, thou contents thy ſelf with thy legall ſallary, who haſt nigh 300 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> by the yeare, and yet thou wouldſt have more, if thou couldſt get it, thou art ſo greedy, as may be well underſtood by thy ſaying: that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115488:19"/>in former time, that the Biſhops and Paſtors had not only a ſetled maintenance of that value, but of a great deal more, which is an unheard off thing in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore thy own mouth confeſt, what greedy Dogs you Preiſt have bin ſince your beginning, &amp; yet with the deceit of thy heart thou wouldſt ſtil cover; but the day doth make you manifeſt, to be ſuch who run, and the Lord never ſent you; and therefore you profit not the people at all: Therefore what is thy teaching and warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the people which thou here boaſts of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art found one of the Dreamers, and ſtudiers, and mutterers, who ſpeaks a Divination of thy own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord, and ſo feeds the people with wind, and aire: therefore ſilence thou deceiver, for going about to excuſe thy ſelfe from theſe things, as if thou waſt more holy then thy Brethren; for in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thy lying and hypocriſie doth but the more appear; and therefore this ſhall ſerve to prove thee a lyer in all the reſt of thy excuſes, and it is not uncharitable, nor cenſorious to tell thee ſo, though thou ſo accuſeſt me; but a lie in thy mouth is no wonder.</p>
               <p>Whether ever thou laboured with thy hands, to make the Goſpel free, and without charge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 15.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> a Miniſter of the Goſpel did.</p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer thou doſt not at all reſolve my Querie; but ſhuffleſt to and fro to hide thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> and excuſe thy ſelfe by pleading <hi>Pauls</hi> power, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. and ſaiſt that Chriſt your Maſter did not injoyne you ſo to doe, which to prove thou quotes <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.7. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.4. and alſo pleades that in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. and alſo pleades a liberty by the Councells and Synods in the Church in former ages, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yet all this doth not prove, that ever thou laboured with thy hands to make the Goſpel free and without charge,<note place="margin">Reply</note> which any who reades theſe Scriptures may ſee and by thy ſilence in the ſame judge thee guilty and to be out of the Apoſtles practice: and therefore theſe Scriptures will witneſſe againſt thee, (which thou haſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115488:20"/>quoted) for thou art not as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waſt called to the Miniſtry as they was, neither preacheſt freely as they did, neither laboureſt with thy hands as <hi>Paul</hi> did, but onely makeſt a trade and a gaine of the Apoſtles words for thy own ends: and therefore what haſt thou to do, to mention Chriſt or his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters who art ſo plainly found out of their practiſe, or to call Chriſt thy Maſter who art thy ſelfe called Maſter and ſo robs him of his honour, and art not in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, (who ſaith, be not ye called Maſters) and ſo art none of his, and therefore haſt nothing to do with that liberty which he hath given to his faithfull labourers whom he himſelfe hath called into his Vineyard: and as for that Scripture in <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.7, it is not againſt labour, but for labour before thou canſt have thy hire, but thou would'ſt have it and be maintained in Idleneſſe by others labours as the Clergy men (as thou calleſt them) in England are, who are no Miniſters of Chriſt who are called of men Maſter, and ſo are out of his doctrine in the ſteps of the Phariſes whom the wo is unto, and therefore in this theſe, Councels and Synods (as thou call'ſt them) in your Church in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages have acted contrary to Scripture, in ordaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that you ſhould not worke, and labour with your hands for your ſelves and your families, but that you ſhould live in Pride and Idleneſſe, by the ſweate of others browes, to be maintained as you are: which ordinance is not of God but of man by which you ſtand, and how haſt thou before falſly accuſed me for not working, though I am not chargeable to the world, and now thou art ſtriveing by Scripture wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and falſe applying and all the waies thou canſt, for to excuſe thy ſelfe from labouring with thy handes, as the Apoſtle did, though thou and thy family are alltogether chargeable to the world. All which Scriptures ſhall ſtand againſt thee, for they all maintaine working be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the benefit of the worke come to them, be it ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115488:20"/>or temporall, for the Oxe treades not out the come without labour: but what corne have you Clergy men trodden forth? and what ſpirituall things have you ſowne? and what Goſpel you have preached, this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares in England? doth not the fruits of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry condemne you, and witneſſe againſt you, to be ſuch as run, and the Lord never ſent you, and ſo the curſe follows you and is upon your Miniſtry, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore profits not the people at all, but as drones lives upon the painefull labour of others, yea though you do not labour with your hands yet who more intangles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the affaires of this world, then you that calls your ſelves Clergy men both by law and cunning craft and deceipt, and bargaining and oppreſſing thereby, to make your ſelves rich with the things of this life, yea what thing is there in this Nation to get riches by, (though never ſo unbeſeeming ſpirituall men) but you have a hand in it, and therefore none of thoſe ſpirituall Souldiers which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. therefore ſilence thou deceiver for medling with the Scripture, with thy Babylonious language (as prohibit, Mechanick, Synod, and Clergy) which are the words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and contrary to the plaine language of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, out of which thou art ſhut, in <hi>Babylon</hi> where thou waſt bred, with thy Clergy as thou calleſt them.</p>
               <p>Whether thou doſt not walke in the ſteps of the Scribes and Phariſes who art called of men Maſter or Doctor, and haſt the cheifeſt ſeate in the Synagogues,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 16.</note> and uppermoſt rooms at feaſts and greetings in the markets contrary to the practiſe of the Apoſtles, and ſo art un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the woe which Chriſt pronounced againſt ſuch, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>And here thou wouldeſt ſhuffle off with Queſtioning inſtead of Anſwering, and ſaiſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> what if Chriſt gave the name of Maſter to Nicodemus, <hi>John.</hi> 3.10 and <hi>Luke</hi> the name of Doctor to <hi>Gamaliel</hi> in <hi>Act,</hi> 5.3.4. and thou ſaiſt, Is it then the giving or taking of theſe names, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115488:21"/>Chriſt forbiddeth or the arrogant uſing of them, out of an high or proud Spirit that deſires to be Idolized? and thou confeſſeſt the word Rabby ſignifies Doctor or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which names thou ſaiſt was familiarly given both in the Old and New Teſtament, which to prove thou quotes, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reply. The <hi>89</hi> and <hi>90,</hi> Que: are anſwered in this Reply; and thy <hi>92</hi> Query alſo.</note>Here thy blindneſſe doth appeare, and thou wilt need no other proofe againſt thee but thy own words, though here thou would'ſt go about to ſlander Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, whom thou art not worthy to name, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doſt thou thereby anſwer my Query, but would juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy that which Chriſt cried woe againſt, &amp; therfore a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Antichriſt art found to which the woe belonges for that Scripture in <hi>John</hi> 3.10. doth not prove that Chriſt called Nicodemus Maſter, as thou wouldeſt faine ſlander him, neither doth that, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.34. prove, that <hi>Luke</hi> gave <hi>Gamaliel</hi> the name of Doctor, but in way of declaration what he was accounted amongſt the Jewes, as any that reades with underſtanding may ſee: yea thou thy ſelfe canſt not deny it, but that thou would'ſt be glad of any thing to ſhelter thy deceipt; but Chriſt expreſly forbids his to be be called Maſter, and therefore it is conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that you take theſe names unto your ſelves, from an arrogancy and pride of Spirit that you might be Idoliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as is well knowne, how you ſwell and are puffed up in wrath and rage, if you be not ſo called by thoſe you account your inferiors; or elſe you would not own it, being Chriſt hath ſo expreſly forbidden it, to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and you profeſſing your ſelves to be his Miniſters; &amp; the word Miniſter ſignifies ſervant; &amp; <hi>Paul,</hi> who was his Miniſter ſaid he made himſelfe ſervant to all, but you would be Maſters over all,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 9.19.</note> bearing rule by your meanes though hired as Servants, yet more unreaſonable &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, for you will have it of them you do no work for: and alſo whatſoever thou ſaiſt Doctor or Maſter ſignifies, Chriſt hath forbidden it, and therefore in uſeing of it thou art out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and the woe is unto thee, and the more for wreſting the Scripture to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115488:21"/>maintaine it, and uphold it which Chriſt hath cried down, and it is well knowne to them that are not wilfully blind, that Maſter or Doctor are names that are given and taken, amongſt you Clergy-men (as you call your ſelves (as Titles of honour; witneſſe your degrees in your Nurſeries of deceipt, (which you call V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities) as firſt Bachellor, then from Bachellor to Maſter of Arts, and from that to Bachellor of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and from that to Doctor of Divinity; which higheſt Title is given to thee, and therefore it is no wonder that thou ſo pleads for it, but the leaſt Child of light, will judge theſe traditions to be upheld by the Pride; and arrogancy of the fleſh that would be Idolized, but the old man muſt needs plead for his life: neither doth theſe Scriptures in, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.38. at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thee, for neither Doctor nor Maſter is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in theſe Scriptures, and thus thou art ignorant of the letter, then far unfit to be a teacher of others which thou doſt aſſume to thy ſelfe by the name of Doctor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy own meaning.</p>
               <p>And as for the cheife ſeates in the ſynagogues and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt roomes at feaſts,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> ſome thou ſaiſt that are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, were allowed them by Chriſt himſelfe which to prove thou quotes, <hi>Lnk.</hi> 14.7.8. <hi>&amp;c. Mark.</hi> 5.22. And by <hi>Luke, Ast.</hi> 13.15. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.8.17. and as for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations they are allowed thou ſaiſt, as well in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket places as any where elſe.</p>
               <p>This is the trueſt word that thou haſt yet ſpoken in one reſpect, though from a falſe Spirit:<note place="margin">Reply.</note> for your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh cuſtoms and ſalutations, are allowed-of no where, by the Scripture, neither haſt thou brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proofe to the contrary, and it is alſo eaſily diſcerned, you rather chuſe them in the markets, or in Pudlique to be ſeene of men, that you might be accounted Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and looked upon for your breeding, witneſſe your congying and bowing, with your hats off in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and Idolizing of one anothers perſons, wherein
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115488:22"/>you exalt your ſelves above the Angel, who would not ſuffer <hi>John</hi> to bow unto him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.8.9.</note> but ſaid, he was his fellow ſervant: therefore let this judge you and condemn you in theſe practiſes, which by you are uſed from an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and an in ordinate deſire of them, and therefore are the moſt unworthy as thou confeſſeſt the Scribes and Phariſes were, and therefore art out of thy own mouth judged,<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.19.</note> although thou wold'ſt caſt it upon the Quakers as thou calleſt them, but we can juſtly cleare our ſelves and caſt it into thy own boſome for we uſe no ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh cuſtoms, yet we can juſtly ſay with <hi>John,</hi> we are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickedneſſe, which thou accounts an exhalting of our ſelves, and in that thou belyeſt Chriſt and the Scriptures in ſaying he allowed theſe things to any (which he cryed downe) thy impudency doth the more appeare that thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not ſtick to bely us, whom thou calleſt Quakers, for none of theſe Scriptures which thou quotes, to uphold the chiefeſt ſeates in the Synagogue &amp; uppermoſt roomes at feaſtes, doth at all concerne the matter, but onely <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.7. &amp;c. which Chriſt ſpoke as a parable to the Phariſes, who loved the uppermoſt roomes at feaſts; which alſo may fitly be applyed to you now who take the uppermoſt reome,<note place="margin">How thy 9th Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. Mat. <hi>20.25, 26, 27.</hi> Jam. <hi>12.</hi> John <hi>13.</hi> John <hi>5.44.</hi>
                  </note> and thinks ſcorne to take the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, which may eaſily be diſcerned by you, with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall eye, or elſe you would not own theſe things, which Chriſt declared againſt, to his Miniſters, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo taught them that he that would be the greateſt, ſhould be the leaſt, and the Apoſtle forbids all reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Chriſt ſhewed an example of humility to his Miniſters, when he waſhed their feet, and condemned the Phariſes who received honour one of another, which thou art here pleading for: then if thou beeſt not in their ſteps, let the underſtanding judge.</p>
               <p>What is the Church and whether it be not a deluſion to the people,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 17.</note> and a diſhonour to Chriſt to call a houſe of lime and ſtone, a Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115488:22"/>
And in thy Anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> thou pleadeſt it a cuſtom in moſt ages, and by a Trope of figure; but thou confeſſeſt the word Church is firſt and properly a congregation of Saints, or of ſuch as profeſſe ſo to be, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. and in the ſecond place thou ſaiſt, this word is uſed for a place where ſuch a Congregation uſe to aſſemble; which to prove thou quotes; <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. and ver. 18. and Chap. 14.5.23. compared with ver. 19.28. neither is this any deluſion to the people thou ſaiſt, nor more diſhonour to God, then to uſe this phraſe, the houſe of God; which to prove thou quotes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.7. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 42.4. therefore here we ſeeke a knot in a bulruſh, thou ſaiſt.</p>
               <p>And thus thou blaſphemer values thy blaſphemy covering it with lies,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> that thou might ſtill keepe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in blindneſſe who makes ſuch a ſmall light matter of it, to put a houſe of lime and ſtone for the body of Chriſt which is the Church, and thus you have long fed the people in blindneſſe with your vaine cuſtoms and traditions, and they put you out of your cuſtoms,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24.</note> and you are vexed and troubled, as the heathen was at <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and ſaid they came to turne the world up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide downe: and then, to cover your blaſphemy and lies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.6.</note> you have Tropes and figures, which is the wiſdom of man to cover lies; and thus you learned ones make uſe of your learning to make lies in hypocriſie contrary to the Scripture, for the Types and Figures in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture figured forth ſomthing to come, but your ſteeple houſes are no figures of Chriſt, nor his body (which is the Church) and when the ſubſtance is come, of what uſe is the figure? for the Temple which God commanded So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon to build him, which was called the houſe of God, (where them that feared the Lord worſhipped him) was a figure of Chriſt, but when Chriſt the ſubſtance came he Propheſied of its deſtruction, <hi>Math.</hi> 24. and <hi>Steven</hi> after him declared againſt it, and by them that upheld, it was ſtoned to death, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.47.48.49. &amp;c: and <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt it and by them that upheld it, was perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115488:23"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24.25. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.26.27. as we are by you now, that uphold your Idolls Temples, that figure forth nothing but the Imaginations of man, neither was ever commanded by God to be built, as <hi>Solomons</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was, which for its time was called the houſe of God; but the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaw the end of it, when he ſpoke that in <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.1, 2. But that you ſhould call your popiſh houſes, the houſe of God, which was built by the Papiſts, and ſuch like, without any Command of God, thou haſt no Scripture proof to maintain it: neither are thoſe fit examples to bring to prove it, as the Schollars and the School, and the Jews and their Synagogues: what doth this at all prove, that you ſhould call your Idolls Temples as the body of Chriſt, which was made of living ſtones, elect and pretious; for the Scripture all along witneſſes, that the Church is the body of Chriſt, which is the Saints, as this Scripture doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which thou haſt quoted in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. but it doth not at all prove thy lie, that the Church is a Congregation of ſuch as profeſs to be Saints; for it is more then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, though with a profeſſion you have long deluded the people: yet many there are that profeſs Chriſt in words, but in life deny him, who are no Saints, nor the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16</note> though thou art blinde, &amp; ſees no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: yet according to thy own meaning, you do not call your Aſſemblies, and the place where your Aſſemblies meets, all one; for you call your meeting places Churches, and the people a Congregation; and ſo here out of thy own mouth thou art judged, yet it would be as much blaſphemy, to call your people a Church, as the place where they meet, a Church; for it is well known, that all manner of unrighteous perſons meets there, as thou confeſſeſt the greateſt part of the profeſſors are earthly minded, as in thy anſwer to my 11th Query; and I am ſure the chiefeſt of them are blind, and led by Cuſtoms and Traditions, as thou here makes it appear, who thy ſelfe haſt been a Teacher ſo long, and now goes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115488:23"/>about to juſtifie it lawful, to call a houſe of lime and ſtone, a Church, which thou goeſt about to prove, by wreſting the Scripture; but let any with a ſingle eye, read theſe Scriptures, which thou haſt quoted in thy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, concerning the Church,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.15 <hi>Act.</hi> 20.16.</note> and ſee if they do at all mention any houſe to be a Church; but only the Saints whoſe bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt; for they commonly met in dwelling houſes; but you call none Churches, but your Steeple-houſes, which hath been your Cuſtom long; and it is well known, how the ignorant people that go to them, have long idolized them as the houſes of God, and looked upon them to be far more holy then any other place, and have envied and hated, and even murthered thoſe in their hearts, that ſhould ſay to the contrary, and you Prieſts have been their great Agents in it, though you have known in your Conſciences to the contrary: yet you know, that where the people are the moſt blinde, you are the more idolized and ſet up; and it is your greateſt grief, where the light appears, as is openly manifeſt by the chief Prieſts, who now rage and rail againſt the light, where it appears, and perſecutes them that holds it forth, that you might, if it were poſſible, put it out, and ſtill uphold your Fathers Kingdom, which is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then you think you are ſafe, and all will be yours; but your Calamity will come on a ſudden, and your downfall is nigh at hand, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.2.3.</p>
               <p>Whether thou, and ſuch as thou, be not the Creepers into houſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 18.</note> who would confine all to your Steeple-houſes, yea or nay.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou grants, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of ſeducers, that creep into houſes, &amp;c. as in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.7. but whether this beſt ſuits with your manner of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ours, thou ſayſt, judge ye; for thou ſayſt, you do not creep into the Churches, who have the doores ſet wide open, and have your Congregations or Aſſemblies publiquely called together by a Bell, and then thou vents
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115488:24"/>forth a deal of frothy ſtuffe, and ſayſt, why muſt your Houſes of Lime and ſtone be called Steeple-houſes, more then the Glaziers Hall, or the Bull and Mouth neare <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> be called a Glaſſe-houſe, a Chimney-houſe, or a Store-houſe, or a Stable-houſe; but thou askeſt, where did Chriſt or his Apoſtles reproach the Synagogues with reproachful names, as we do your Churches.</p>
               <p>Here thy malitious and ſcornful ſpirit is much more made manifeſt,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> together with thy folly and ignorance, ſo that I am able to judge thee, and the reſt of the Pariſh Preachers, to be thoſe creepers into houſes, that <hi>Paul</hi> there ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.7. who have led ſilly women and people captive theſe many years, full of ſin, and led away with divers luſts, who ſome have learned 40. years, ſome 50. ſome 60. yea ſome 80. and yet ſtrangers to the truth, yea as blinde and carnall as ever they was, ſo that they take a Houſe of Lime and ſtone for a Church and a Houſe of God, as you have taught: and aske them why they call it ſo, and they will anſwer, it was called ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they was born, and will be after they were dead: then judge ye, whether theſe Creatures be not blind and carnall, and led by your own Cuſtoms and traditions, and you are their Teachers, who would bear rule in your Steeple-houſes, ſo that none ſhall ſpeak but your ſelves: if they do, you have a Law to lay upon them, contrary to the order of the true Church, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30, 31, 32. That all might ſpeak one by one; and if any thing be revealed to him that ſtands by, let the firſt hold his peace; but this is called diſorder amongſt you, that call your ſelves Saints, and are not, but the Synagogue of Satan; and by thy own Confeſſion are led together by a Bell; for which you have no Rule in the Scripture, and ſo you lead them by Cuſtom and Tradition; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thy own words here proves what I ſaid in my laſt Reply, that you do not call your Aſſemblies, and the place where your Aſſemblies meets both by one; for here thou calleſt the place a Church, and the people the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115488:24"/>Congregation, as I ſaid before; and thou blinde guide, where doſt thou read in the Scripture of Church-doores be aſhamed and bluſh, thus to preſume in thy blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and therefore how ſoever thou have taken theſe houſes to be, wherein deceivers creeps, as before is proved, and have taught the people ſo, to put them out of jealouſie of you to be the deceivers, doth not at all excuſe you from it; for the Apoſtle himſelf taught in private houſes and Chambers, and private places;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 20.20.</note> and therefore by that account, thou would tax the Apoſtle to be a deceiver, if he was here, as thou doſt <hi>James Parnel,</hi> and thoſe whom thou ſcornfully calls his gang: but where doſt thou finde ſuch a word in the Scripture, which proceeds out of thy malitious and evill heart; but thy reproaches unto us are riches, (and thy ſhame.) And the Reaſon why thoſe Houſes near <hi>Alderſgate</hi> (which thou ſo ſpits thy venom at, becauſe the people of God have uſed to meet there,) may not be called (as thou in contempt doſt terme them) as well as your Stone-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be called, Steeple-houſes, is, becauſe they have names fitting for them already, for to diſtinguiſh them from other places; and ſo alſo the word Steeple-houſe, is the fitteſt name to diſtinguiſh your meeting places from others, and alſo to take from them that holy name, which only belongs to the body of Chriſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to wear out that Idolatry of the peoples mindes, which they through long Cuſtom have born to thoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous places: neither do we any more reproach them in ſo ſaying, then Chriſt and his Apoſtles did, in calling the Jews meeting places, Synagogues, though thou highly diſhonoureſt Chriſt in calling them Churches, which ſignifies his body: Have you no other names to beſtowe upon your ſtone houſes, and high places; but moſt blaſphemouſly to call them by the name of God's, and holy men, whom you are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to name, as you call your Colledges, (which are Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of Satan, and Cages of unclean Birds,) by the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115488:25"/>name of <hi>Immanuel,</hi> and by the name of Chriſt and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the like: if you had called them by the name of Glaziers Hall, or Bull and Mouth, or Synagogue, and the like: we ſhould not gainſay it, and therefore in this, the Jews will condemn you, who did not preſume to call their meeting places, by ſuch holy names, as you preſumptuouſly do, which is, and hath been a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the people to Idolatry, to idolize the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe of their names which was given to them by the Papiſts, who ignorantly worſhip names, and you caſt out the Papiſts for Idolatry, and yet upholds their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls: therefore woe unto you blinde guides, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luders of the people, your wickedneſs is had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance before the Lord.</p>
               <p>Whether it was the practice of the Apoſtles, to take a Text of the Prophets words,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 19.</note> and from thence to raiſe uſes, points, Traills and motives, as thou and ſuch as thou doſt, who makes a Trade of their words.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> thou ſayſt, that it hath been the practice of the Church and her Teachers this many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years; (for the which thou haſt no Scripture proof) and thirdly, thou ſayſt, that none will deny, that this is an uſeful and profitable way of teaching, (which is an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable lie, which I, and hundreds more can teſtifie againſt) And fourthly thou ſayſt, it may be proved out of the Scriptures, that all this hath been done by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, (which is another lie; and thoſe are the Scriptures upon which thou wouldſt ground thy lies, in which they will witneſs againſt thee, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.31. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.35. and for to maintain thy uſes, points, Trialls and motives, thou quotes <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.17. <hi>John</hi> 8.31. and 13.35. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34.</p>
               <p>Oh thou lier,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> thy lies will not cover thee, nor the Scripture ſtand for thee, who art found out of the life and practice of them that gave them forth, who art one of the lying falſe Teachers, who have deluded the people
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115488:25"/>this many hundred years,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</note> which deluded ones are your Church, amongſt whom you have uſed your Philoſophy, and vain deceipt, by which you have long ſpoiled them, ſo that the greateſt part of the profeſſors therein are earthly minded, by thy own confeſſion; and I am ſure that another part are Drunkards, and ſwearers, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, and ſcoffers, and ſcorners, and proud and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious ones, and the like; and now where is the fruits and profitableneſs of your teaching? therefore for ſhame ſtop thy mouth for boaſting of your Church, and her teachers, and ſaying, None will deny the profitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your teaching; for, like people, like Prieſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</note> as the Prophet ſaid; and you are the heaps of teachers, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the world, and draw itching eares after you, (who cannot endure ſound Doctrine) with your fained enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing words of mens wiſdom; but the Teacher of the true Church is but one, which is its head, even Chriſt, who ſpeaks with Power and Authority, (and not as you Scribes) whoſe teaching is a profitable teaching, as is much witneſſed in theſe latter dayes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.29.</note> to your great ſhame and grief, who have been the profeſſed Teachers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> this many years: neither doth any of theſe Scritpures prove, that ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles took a Text of Scripture; and by humane art and ſtudy, did raiſe Uſes, Points, Trialls and Motives, as you do, which is a commendable teaching,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4</note> by the wiſe ones of the world, who know not the wiſdom of God; but to them the preaching of the Croſſe is fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs, as was accounted amongſt the <hi>Greeks,</hi> becauſe the Apoſtle came not with entiſing words of mens wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, (as you do to pleaſe men) but in plainneſs of ſpeech, ſpoke the word of the Lord faithfully, and alſo ſaid, If he yet ſought to pleaſe men, he ſhould not be the Servant of Chriſt;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> but this is all your care, whoſe truſt is in man and not in Chriſt: and in all thoſe Scriptures, when Chriſt or his Apoſtles ſpoke of a Text of Scripture, out of the old Teſtament, it was to ſhew the fulfilling
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115488:26"/>thereof, or to witneſs to what they had ſaid; but you will take theſe Scriptures, for to give your carnall mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and interpretations of them, and ſo from them ſpeak a divination of your own brain, for gain and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre; and this is the uſe you make of theſe points, as thou calles them, which the Scriptures before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned will not at all maintain, and yet thou canſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently quote this Scripture in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25.34. which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids taking thought what to eat, what to drink, and wherewithall to be cloathed, when it is ſo publickly known, that it is your greateſt care, and that which thou haſt been here much labouring to maintain all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, to prove it lawful, for thee to take nigh 200. or 300. pounds by the year, of the world: yea and for a Law to compell them, if they refuſe to give it; and yet thou art not aſhamed to ſay, that thou doſt not go in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for gifts and rewards; and the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Scripture which thou haſt here quoted, will witneſs againſt thee, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. which ſaith, the Scripture was given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for reproof, for correction, and inſtruction in righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfected, throughly furniſhed unto every good work; but thou hates to be reproved, and calles them foul-mouthed currs, and the like, that do reprove thee, and thou teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt for Doctrine, the traditions of men, as to call a houſe of Lime and Stone, a Church and the like, as is before proved.</p>
               <p>And how have you by all your Doctrines, reproof, correction, and inſtruction, this many years perfected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, when as the profeſſors therein are earthly minded (as thou ſayſt;<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note>) and you that are therefore Teachers the moſt of all, and moſt of you denies perfection in this life; and though thou with thy tongue profeſs it; yet in life denies it, which is worſt of all, and ſo I take thee: and though thou haſt been ſo pleading for thy way, yet thou ſayſt, you would change it for a better, if any can
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115488:26"/>ſhew it you, and make your hearers beleive, that it would be more advantages for them, but thou ſaiſt this trade of interpreting the Scripture is an old and a good trade, which to prove thou quotes <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.23: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.2, 3. <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p>Here thou blind guide,<note place="margin">Reply,</note> thy nakedneſſe is open to the world, and thy hearers may conſider it who have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon thee as their Teacher this many yeares, and yet thou thy ſelfe ſtill to learne which is the beſt way, when as there is but one true way, then thou who art igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this true way, muſt needs be in a falſe way: then how haſt thou deluded thy hearets this many yeares,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39.</note> and alſo belyed thy ſelfe in thy Booke? And if the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher be ever learning, then what muſt the herers of ſuch a one be, let the wiſe-hearted judge; and I beleive and know, that your hearers would ſoone beleive the ſame, if the Preachers of truth might have liberty to ſpeake, when they come amongſt you: but if any come in that intent, you are ready to ſet your people upon them to hale them out with force, and alſo you have a law to caſt them into Priſon, as many of us do witneſſe at this day: and therefore thou liar, the convincing of your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of a better way, is not your greateſt care, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your greateſt feare, leaſt any ſhould be drawne from you, and ſo your trade come to faile (as thou calleſt it): but this I know is your greateſt care, that any body would ſhew you, a better way to get mony by, and alſo perſwade your hearers into it, (or elſe thou thinks, you are never the better) and then you would leave inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the Scripture, which now thou calles a good trade, but thou Marchant of <hi>Babylon,</hi> where doth any of theſe Scriptures which thou haſt quoted, prove or terme interpreting the Scripture, a trade? though you Marchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> make a trade of it, to get lucre by, and ſo call it a trade, who think gaine is godlineſs: but well may others accuſe you, for making a trade and a gaine of the Scriptures, while you your ſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115488:27"/>it, and thus thou wreſts the Scripture, for thine own ends and paints thy work with Scripture, for to make the ignorant believe it is grounded upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: oh be aſhamed to take it into thy mouth, to make a trade of it, which was freely ſpoken forth by the holy men of God as they was moved by the Holy-Ghoſt, and thou makes the people believe, it is of ſome private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and ſo thou makes Marchandize of the people, and ſo out of thy own mouth art judged to be a lier, who before denied it.</p>
               <p>Whether thou doſt ſpeake as thou art moved by the Holy-Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 20,</note> as they did, who ſpoke forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſai'ſt that thou haſt anſwered to this allready,<note place="margin">P. Anſ</note> that thou uſually doſt ſpeake at the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or aſſiſtance of the Holy-Ghoſt, thou praiſes God for it.</p>
               <p>But thou hypocrite I have alſo in this already proved thee a lier,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reply.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4</note> and thy God to be the Father of lies, who is the God of the blind world, in which thou art a blind guide, and an enemy to the Holy-Ghoſt, where he is witneſſed to rule, and this <hi>James Parnel</hi> and thoſe thou calls his fellows, can diſcerne in thee though thou art blind and cannot them ſee.</p>
               <p>What Scripture haſt thou for ſprinkling Infants with water on their faces?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 21</note> and whether all are Chriſtians and in the faith of Chriſt, that are ſo done by, or what doth it profit?</p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> the deceipt of thy heart thou ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo that the ſimple may eaſily diſcerne the folly, and alſo ſee how thou and the reſt of thy bretheren, have deluded and bewitched the Nation, for thou ſay'ſt thou holdes not the Baptiſm of infants abſolutely neceſſary but lawfull only, and to prove the lawfulneſſe of it thou ſay'ſt, it is ſufficient, that thou haſt no command in the Scripture againſt the ſprinkling of infants in the face with baptiſmal water, but thou ſay'ſt thou haſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Governours, &amp; thou art commanded to be ſubject to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115488:27"/>
Here the people now may ſee how they have been long deluded, for thy own mouth utters it,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> for when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many of the people of this Nation who follow you blind guides, have perſwaded themſelves through your evill incenſing, and leavening of their minds to this day, this to be abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, and that their Children could not be ſaved, if they died without it: and now thou comes to the Triall, to prove it, thou confeſſeſt it is not neceſſary, but lawfull onely, and that is becauſe there is no command of God againſt it, thou ſay'ſt: neither a command for it, but by man; and thus you have long deluded the nations, with your own Inventions, for the which you have no Scripture, then how is it your rule? here you run beſides your rule, teaching for doctrine the commandements and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, which the Scripture is againſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt infants baptiſm, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.22.23. which by thy own confeſſion is but an ordinance of man,<note place="margin">Here thy <hi>53.</hi> Que. is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> but God is to be obeyed rather then man, and you do it not for the Lords ſake, but for to pleaſe man: for the Lord doth not require it at your hands, and now all the ignorant people who have beene in this bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you, may ſee your blindneſſe who have long made them believe that it was an ordinance of Chriſt, that their Children ſhould be ſprinkled (and one of the points of ſalvation) (as you call them) and now nothing but an ordinance of man, which will not ſtand for thee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for in that thou lieſt alſo, to ſay it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of thy governours, for in that they leave every one to the liberty of their conſciences, and all lawes and ordinances afore time to the contrary are made by this nul and voyd: and now, doth the Holy-Ghoſt teach thee to lie? oh thou lier and blaſphemer of the holy-Ghoſt, who ſaid that uſually thou ſpeakeſt by the motion of the Holy-Ghoſt, and now art taken in a lie: oh Satan is high in thee, and thy wickedneſſe is great, and which doſt thou call thy baptiſmall water,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115488:28"/>this alſo is the deceipt of thy heart, and that which is not of ſaith is ſin,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> therefore infants baptiſm: for you ſay your faith is grounded upon Scripture, then where is your Scripture for infants baptiſm, and thus out of the doctrine of Chriſt you are found, acting and doing your own workes, and therfore the reſt of thy pretended an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer I ſhall leave to the impartiall reader to judge of; wherein thou haſt much manifeſted thy ignorance and bindneſſe, and in vaine haſt thou quoted any Scripture: for if any of it would ſtand for infants baptiſm, then it would be neceſſary, which thou confeſſeſt it is not, and therefore thou Serpent why wreſteſt thou the Scripture, thus to uphold that which is not neceſſary, and where as thou ſpeakeſt of the promiſes made in the ſeed (but that ſeed is not the ſeed of the Serpent, which rules in all you Children of diſobedience, therefore) what haſt thou to do with the promiſes, and where doſt thou prove that infants baptiſm is the ſeal of the covenant or the badge of the Kingdom, as thou termeſt it: but thou liar, read what the ſeal is, in <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. and with that ſtop thy mouth. And whereas thou ſpeakeſt of Chriſts calling little Children,<note place="margin">Here thy <hi>54,</hi> and <hi>55.</hi> Qu. is Anſ. John. <hi>4.2</hi> Eph. <hi>2.3.</hi> John. <hi>3.3</hi>
                  </note> what of that? Chriſt baptiſed none; therefore ſilence babler: And how are your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſanctifyed from the wombe, (as thou ſay'ſt <hi>John</hi> was) when as all are by Nature the Children of wrath, and except they be borne againe, they cannot enter, and therefore thou manifeſts, that your Church is made up of unregenerate perſons, into which thou ſaiſt they are admitted by water, and 20 or 30 yeares after they are thus baptiſed, you preach repentance to them, and this is the cauſe why the profeſſors therein are earthly minded, as thou complaineſt, and therefore no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian parents but blind carnall creatures, who thinks it profits their Children to be admitted into ſuch a Church: and as the Children grow up, they ſhow what ſeal you have given them, which is more like the marke of the beaſt then the ſeal of the covenant, and therefore
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115488:28"/>your prayers which thou talkeſt of, are an abomination and availeth not, and thus haſt thou foamed out thy ſhame and folly, to the ſight of all but thoſe who are blind and love to have it ſo, for here is one of the maine points of your religion proved a meere deluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Qu. <hi>22.</hi> P. Anſ.</note>What is the eſtate and condition of a Chriſtian?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer, thou haſt ſtolen the Apoſtles words, which he ſpeaks concerning this matter, and ſays, There are three ages, ſteps, and degrees of Chriſtianity; And the firſt Age, ſtep, and Degree thou confeſſeſt is in Chriſt, and begotten of the Father in the hatred of ſin, and love of righteouſneſs, and by him brought to the knowledge of Redemption, from all iniquity, and Renovation in all righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Here thou haſt deſtroyed the whole faith of your vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church; for they generally believe,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> that they ſhall never be wholly ſet free from all iniquity, nor be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in righteouſneſs, while they are upon the earth; and if this be the loweſt eſtate of Chriſtianity, to be in Chriſt, and redeemed from all iniquity, and begotten by the Father, and renewed in all righteouſneſs, (which is perfection in righteouſneſs) then by thy own confeſſion none of them are Chriſtians, neither thou who art a teacher of them; for thou haſt been openly found in ſin and iniquity, as in lying, covetouſneſs, lightneſs, ſcornfulneſs, oppreſſion, and deceipt, as before is proved; and now thou art again found a lier, in ſaying, that we know not the firſt eſtate of a Chriſtian from the laſt; but we are able to diſcern thee, yet uncome to the firſt, and therefore far off the laſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in years an old man: yet a Child can tell thee thy confuſion, therefore ſtop thy mouth thou deceiver, and ſit thee down and conſider, how thou and thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have for this many years deceived this Nation, and labour thy ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes, leaſt the Lord in thy deſtruction make thee an example to all thy Brethren-deceivers.</p>
               <p>What doth the faith which thou profeſſeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 23.</note> differ
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115488:29"/>from the faith of the Hypocrite, and what is the faith of the Hypocrite?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſayſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> thy faith is A truſt in the Lord Jeſus, to be holpen up again from the fall, or to be ſaved from the hand of thine enemies, or of all that hate thee, and ſo to be renewed; through him, to be inabled to ſerve him, chearfully and without fear, in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him, all the dayes of thy life; and thou ſayſt, this faith brings forth obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and purifies the heart, and makes you confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to Jeſus, ſo that thou hopes for no benefit by his death, unleſs thou dieſt with him, to all known ſins: but the faith of the Hypocrite, ſeeks all wayes ſomething by or through Chriſt, than what it ſhould ſeek, (to wit) the putting off the old man, and the putting on the new, which is created after God in righteouſneſs, and true holineſs; and herein thou ſayſt, doth thy Faith differ from the Faith of the Hypocrite, and perhaps from <hi>James Parnell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea it doth,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> for my faith is, that there is no putting off the old man, and putting on the new, but by and through Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</note> which is no more then what I ſhould believe: and thy faith which is contrary, is the faith of the Hypocrite, which will periſh; yea and out of thy own mouth I ſhall prove it; for by thy own confeſſion, thou art ſtill in the fall, in ſaying, that thou truſteſt in the Lord Jeſus, to be holpen up out of the fall again: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is concluded, that thou art ſtill in the fall; for if thou waſt holpen already out of the fall, then thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt have the end of thy hope; but its like this faith, thou haſt profeſſed this many years, and haſt been a Teacher ſo long, and yet it hath not brought thee out of the fall; and therefore it is but a borrowed faith, and moſt of thoſe expreſſions thou haſt ſtolen out of <hi>Luke</hi> 1.71.72, 73, 74, 75. which hath not purified thy heart from lies and deceipt: neither art thou in obedience, or conformable to Jeſus Chriſt, who abides not in his
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115488:29"/>doctrine, but teacheſt for doctrine the traditions of men neither art thou dead with him unto all knowne ſins, for this is one to depart from his doctrine, and ſuch hath not God: and this is proved againſt thee in many things, as in taking thy Tithes and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, of the peoples labours, which many of them its like do want it themſelves, which is a great ſin and oppreſſion: and ſecondly in ſprinkling infants which is a great deluſion to the people; and many other things which is before proved againſt thee, which that in thy conſcience cannot but teſtify againſt. And to prove ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word, which thou calleſt the ingiven and Inſpoken word thou quoteſt, <hi>Jer,</hi> 2.1. and 4.11, 13. and to prove another word which thou calleſt the out ſpoken word thou quotes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.11. and to prove another word, which thou calleſt the written word of the Lord thou quoteſt 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16,</p>
               <p>Here thy ignorance of God is not hid,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> who by thy wit and deceiptfull wiſdom would make four of one: but all theſe Scriptures which thou haſt quoted doth not prove any other then one,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29.</note> which word was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning by which all things was made, which thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeſt to be eternall powerfull and living, and that word which came unto the Prophets was as a fire and a hammer to beat the Rocks in peices,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> then was it not powerfull and living, and one and the ſame with that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of which is quick and powerfull,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.1 1.</note> and ſharper then a two edged ſword, and this is the ſame word of life which the Apoſtles ſpoke from and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which was from the beginning,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.</note> and this was the ſame word which was publiſhed, which <hi>David</hi> there ſpeaks of; and by this word was the Prophets all begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and borne againe, and this word is inviſible, hid from the carnall eye, as thou thy ſelfe confeſſeſt though in confuſion, but that Scripture which thou quoteſt in the 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. to prove a written word, doth not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115488:30"/>any ſuch thing; but if thou meaneſt that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is that written word, I anſwer there are many words in the Scripture; but the word is but one, of which the Scriptures beares Teſtimony. And thus thy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is manifeſted, and returned into thy own boſom,</p>
               <p>What is the end of Chriſts coming and what is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou goeſt about to prove that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-fould which is but one,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> and ſo runs into thy ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry diviſions in thy imaginations: and though thou accuſeſt <hi>James Parnel,</hi> that he knows it not, yet he is able to diſcerne thy confuſion, for in one place, thou ſay'ſt there is a redemption from all ſinne, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther redemption from all evill, and this thou calls two-fold; and thou ſay'ſt there is a redemption from the curſe of the law, and another redemption from the guilt of ſin, which alſo thou calleſt two-fold.</p>
               <p>How many redemptions wouldeſt thou here make, of one,<note place="margin">Reply,</note> thou blind guide? Can any be redeemed from all ſin? and not from all evill, and from the curſe of the law, and not from the guilt of ſin? and is not all this one, and by one, and fulfilled in one? But it may eaſily be concluded that thou canſt witneſſe none of this; for ſo long as thou art in the fall, thou art under the curſe of the law, and the guilt of ſin, as before out of thy own mouth is proved; and they that can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this redemption, are Chriſtians indeed, and cleaſn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from earthly mindedneſſe: all which thou nor thy Church is not, as before out of thy own mouth is prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but are ſtill in your iniquity upholding the works of the Devill, and are not ſaved from your enemies that are of your own houſe; neither is the righteouſneſſe of the Law fulfilled in you, neither is your ſouls deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the houſe of bondage, neither is Jeſus your high Prieſt, who ſet up your ſelves to be Prieſts in his ſtead, holding up the changeable Prieſt-hood which took Tithes, and ſo denies Chriſt come in the fleſh and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115488:30"/>ſhall be judged by him, whom thou confeſſeſt is the judge of the world, all which thou ſay'ſt is the end of Chriſts coming.</p>
               <p>Whether thou wilt own that Chriſt hath enlightened every one that cometh into the world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 30.</note> and whether they that know that light need any man to teach them, and whether thou leadeſt up any under thy Miniſtry, that they need not thee to teach them.</p>
               <p>And in thy anſwer thou confeſſeſt that Chriſt doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every one that cometh into the world,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> becauſe the Apoſtle affirmes it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. And ſecondly thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeſt, that they which have attained to the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this light, need not that any man ſhould teach them for they are ſufficiently taught of God, thou ſay'ſt <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. But thou ſay'ſt thou denieſt that we are ſo taught, or in ſuch a meaſure; but thou ſay'ſt till that full light ſhine in you, you may have other helps and teachers which to prove, thou quoteſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thou deceiver! thou run, and the Lord never ſent thee, who hath beene a teacher of the people, and a profeſſor of the light ſo many yeares, and haſt not yet brought any of thy hearers to the knowledge of the light; yea thou numbereſt thy ſelfe, amongſt them whom this full light doth not yet ſhine, but ſtands in need of other helps, and teachers: then, thou hypocrite and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, how ſhouldſt thou teach thy hearers the full know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the light, (as thou ſay'ſt they will witneſſe for thee) when as thou thy ſelfe ſtands in need to be taught it, by thy own confeſſion? Therefore it may well be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that thou knoweſt not that Chriſt hath enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened every one that cometh into the world neither wouldeſt confeſſe it, but that the Apoſtle affirmes it, in that Scripture which thou quoteſt in <hi>John</hi> 1.9. yea that Scripture which thou quoteſtin, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. doth witneſſe againſt thee, and thy hearers to be yet ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115488:31"/>to the promiſes: therefore thou hypocrite how haſt thou belyed thy own conſcience, in ſaying that thou would'ſt bring them to the knowledge of the light, that they ſhould not need thee or any man to teach them, when as that is it, thou openly ſtriveſt againſt; for then thy <hi>Dianah</hi> would bring thee in no gaine, which is thy greateſt care to uphold, and this is witneſſed in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for a truth againſt thee; yea and this Scripture, which thou quoteſt in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20. will witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee to be a lier of the Apoſtle, for that ſpeakes of the world within which ſhines as a light in a dark place which thou art not, yet come to know, and therefore thou denies the truth, but I tell thee we are in that meaſure of light, ſo that we are able to comprehend thee, and ſhew thee thy confuſion, and deceipt; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſilence, from bringing the Prophets or Apoſtles for thy proofe, for they teſtify againſt ſuch as thee, who pretendeſt to teach others, and to be a guide to the blind, a light of them which are in darkneſſe, and an inſtructer of the fooliſh,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.19.20.</note> and art not yet taught thy ſelfe but art dark and blind, and ignorant of the light, and wants inſtruction thy ſelfe: by thy own confeſſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what an impudent lyer art thou, who before ſaid thou uſely ſpoke by the motion of the holy-Ghoſt, and guided by an infallible Spirit, and now not come to that full knowledge of the light that thou needeſt no man to teach thee: but the Prophets and Apoſtles was come to that before they was made teachers, and they by the effect of their Miniſtry turned many from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to light,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 8.5.1 <hi>Jonn.</hi> 2 22.31. <hi>Que.</hi>
                  </note> and brought them to the knowledge of the Anointing ſo that they needed no man to teach them therefore ſilence thou deceiver, for thy bleſſings is curſes, and therefore profits not the people at all.</p>
               <p>Whether they be not the deceivers, that cry Loe here, and loe there, that draw people to look at a Chriſt, in a Heaven far off, without them, or at a <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> far off
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115488:31"/>without them, when as they that cannot witneſs Chriſt in them are Reprobates.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer, thou confeſſeſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> that they that cannot witneſs Chriſt in them, are in a Reprobate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: but thou confeſſeſt, that thou wilt not ſay, that all who ſpeak of a Chriſt within them, ſhall be ſaved, yet thou grants, that thoſe Teachers who points only at a Chriſt without them, or to any other ſpiritual Kingdom of God, then what muſt be within, ſaying, Loe here is Chriſt, and loe there is his Kingdom, may be both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and deceived themſelves for the preſent.</p>
               <p>Herein thou condemneſt thy Brethren,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and deceived, who are ſet up, unpheld, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, by the ſame earthly power as thou art, who are ſuch as cry all, lo here and loe there without, and wholly draw the peoples mindes without, from the light within them, that ſhould lead them to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt and his Kingdom, incenſing them that it is natural, and inſufficient; and though thou doſt here profeſs to the contrary, yet art out, of thy own mouth, judged to be out of the ſtate of ſalvation, who only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeſt Chriſt within, yet art found as deep in ſin and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, and as void of Chriſt or his Light, as the reſt of thy Brethren, who art doting without, as before out of thy mouth is ſufficiently proved, and ſo thy ſelfe art the greateſt deceiver, only the Serpents ſubtlety more reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; but that thou accuſeſt us, that we cry, loe here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people called Quakers, Chriſt a lone is to be found; Thou art a lier, and ſpeakeſt not from an infallible ſpinit, but from a lying ſpirit, which many can witneſs againſt; yet they that are of God heare, as he that can receive it let him.</p>
               <p>Whether they be not out of the faith of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 32.</note> that receive honour, or reſpect perſons?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſayſt, men may receive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and yet be in the faith of Chriſt, which to prove,<note place="margin">P. Anſw,</note>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115488:32"/>thou quoteſt <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.19, 20.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1, 2, 3.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. and many other which doth not at all concerne the matter of my Query; yea thou ſayſt, men may reſpect perſons, and be in the faith, which to prove thou quoteſt <hi>Act.</hi> 26.25. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. but thou confeſſeſt it is a great hinderance to the faith, and the believing in the true word, for men to ſeek the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of men, more then the honour that comes from God, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. And thou ſayſt, it is alſo a blot and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh to the true Believers, to reſpect the ungodly, that are great and rich in this world, before the true Saints that are poor; yea thou ſayſt, it is a plain deniall of the faith, and a good conſcience alſo, to reſpect perſons in doing of juſtice, whether for favour or reward, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p>All theſe Scriptures which thou haſt here quoted,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> doth not at all juſtifie the earthly honour, which you earthly ones give and receive one of another: neither was theſe things written to the world, as thou makes uſe of them; neither did thoſe whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, ſeek after, or receive earthly honour, as you do, who are called of men Maſter, who are ſet up in the chief ſeats of the Synagogues and love greetings in the markets and uppermoſt Rooms at feaſts, and all the earthly honour as may be: all which Chriſt declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt to the Phariſees, and judged them to be in the unbelief; in whoſe ſteps ye are found, and therefore in the unbelief alſo: neither doth any ſuch earthly honour belong to any vertue or grace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 5.4 42, 43, 44 <hi>Act.</hi> 26.31, 32. <hi>Ast.</hi> 24.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 22.22.</note> for Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt it; but they that honour God, them will God honour: neither doth any of theſe Scriptures which thou haſt quoted, juſtifie the reſpect of perſons, which the Apoſtle declared againſt in <hi>James</hi> 2. neither did <hi>Paul</hi> reſpect the perſon of <hi>Feſtus,</hi> when he called him Noble <hi>Feſtus;</hi> for in that he did not adore his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor bow to, nor worſhip it; but <hi>Feſtus</hi> did that which was noble towards <hi>Paul,</hi> and judged him not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115488:32"/>worthy to ſuffer bonds according to their Law: which few of the Rulers of theſe dayes will do; but rather will wreſt and pervert their Law to their own wills, to perſecute thoſe that now are in <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, and guided by <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit, and ſuch they now call peſtilent fellows, and raiſers of ſedition, and adjudge them not worthy to live amongſt men, though they have nothing more againſt them, than the Heathen had againſt <hi>Paul;</hi> and notwithſtanding, all this doth not juſtifie your ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, worſhipping, and reſpecting mens perſon, having them in admiration for advantage ſake, yea though wicked corrupt men, though you do not ſee it, becauſe the gift blindes your eye) for they that are proud and perſecuters, are wicked and corrupt, and by ſuch you are ſet up, upheld and maintained, and therefore adore and worſhip their perſons, having them in admiration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this advantage; but the poor Saints are both by you and them perſecuted and deſpiſed, and you joyn together againſt them, becauſe they cannot worſhip the Beaſt and his Image as you do;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8.</note> and thus out of thy own mouth, art thou judged; and that Scripture which thou quoteſt in <hi>James</hi> 2. will witneſs againſt thee, and that alſo in <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. for it is well known, that you profeſſed Miniſters have been the greateſt actors ever, in ſtirring up the Rulers to perſecute the innocent, yea any in whom the appearance of God was manifeſted, in teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt your deceitful wayes: and the Rulers through favour and reſpect to you, have and do act in their corrupt wills, contrary to all Law or equity againſt ſuch, and have oppreſſed the ſtrangers as Vagabonds and idle fellows, though the Law of the Nation allow them liberty, being free-born in it, which to this day is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed in divers places of the Nation, which that of God in your Conſciences will alſo witnes: &amp; ſuch as thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves neither honor nor reſpect, but muſt periſh in their iniquity; but in thou accuſed us to deny deſerved honour and reſpect to be lawful is a very falſhood, for we honour and reſpect Juſtice, grace, ertue, and all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115488:33"/>in our hearts; but you that are blind put injuſtice, for juſtice, and evill for good, and turn the grace of God, into laciviouſneſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20 <hi>Qu.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Jude</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou own trembling and quaking now, yea on nay?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> thou ſeems to own it in words, alſo ſtealing others expreſſions out of the Scripture, to anſwer my Query; but thy life doth not ſteal it, neither doſt thou own it where it is witneſſed, but makes a ſcoffe at it, as before is proved; and thy ignorance of the ſame may eaſily be diſcerned, (in this thy Anſwer) by any who have taſted of the power of God, who are come to the earths trembling and quaking; and whereas thou denies to tremble and ſhake, as <hi>John Gilpin</hi> and others did, comparing them with the man poſſeſſed with the unclean ſpirit, in <hi>Mark</hi> 9.20. and to be a Quaker al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thou denieſt.</p>
               <p>Thou never waſt a true Quaker yet,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> as may eaſily be diſcerned, by this thy diſcourſe of it, who judgeſt by Reports; and compares the power of God unto an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirit, which power made the Devills to tremble in <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> unto which thou art not yet come; though <hi>John Gilpin</hi> from that departed, and followed the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, and ſo was led into deep deceipt and Imitation, and ſo gave occaſion to ſuch as thee, who wait for occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to blaſpheme the truth, and ſpeak evil of the things thou knoweſt nothing of, but by Reports, which if the true fear of God was in thy heart placed, thou durſt not do: therefore thou and <hi>John Gilpin</hi> ſhall receive your reward, where thou ſhalt quake for ever, if thou doſt not ſpeedily repent, and own the truth which in thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is witneſſed: but thoſe others of ours, whom thou accuſeſt, thou doſt not nominate; and therefore accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt thou knoweſt not who: but any ſuch foaming at the mouth, and the like, which thou here ſpeaks of, we do deny, and returns it into thy own boſom, who art foam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out thy own ſhame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115488:33"/>
What is the pure Religion, and whether in it thou dwelleſt?<note place="margin">34. <hi>Qu.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer, thou haſt nothing to ſay,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> but what thou ſtealeſt out of the Scripture, from their experience, who ſpoke it forth, and thou quoteſt that in <hi>James</hi> 1.27. which ſaith, the pure Religion and undefiled before God, is this, to viſit the Widdows and fatherleſs in their affliction, and to keep themſelves unſpotted of the world, and thou alſo quoteſt that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.33.38.39, 40. and ſaith, It is to love the Lord our God, with all our hearts, minde and might, and our Neighbour as our ſelves; and in this Religion thou ſayſt, thou deſireſt to dwell, and walk, and remain for ever, without being ſhaken.</p>
               <p>But thou muſt be much ſhaken before thou comeſt into this Religion; for thou haſt not yet proved,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> that thou art yet in it; but theſe Scriptures which thou haſt here quoted, will witneſs againſt thee, to be a ſtranger to it, though it is an eaſie thing for to ſet down others Declarations, when they are before thee; but how doſt thou keep thy ſelfe unſpotted of the world, when as thou art drowned in, and art ſo greedy of it, that thou careſt not how thou getteſt it, ſo thou getteſt it, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſufficiently proved out of thy own mouth, and haſt been all along labouring contrary to Scripture, to juſtifie thy taking of gifts and Rewards of the world: and how doſt thou viſit the Widdows and fatherleſs, unleſs it be for thy Tithes, or that they have to maintain thee, and ſo rather to add affliction upon them? or what doſt thou do in this kinde, but thou haſt a ſelfe-end in it, let that in thy Conſcience judge thee; and if thou didſt love the Lord God with all thy heart, thou wouldſt not have thy heart ſo in the earth, thus to delude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive peoples ſouls for gain and lucre, and to take away the fruits of their labours by compulſion, (if they will not give it thee) though thou doſt nothing for them, as before is proved againſt thee, to thy ſhame and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115488:34"/>of face; and thus thy heart is adulterated from God into the earth,<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.15.</note> and the love of God abides not in thee, who art in love with the world; and thus thou loves thy Neighbour as thy ſelfe, when for ſelfes-ſake thou wouldſt deſtroy him both body and ſoul; and thus I need no other weapon to cut off thy head, then what thou thy ſelfe bringeſt.</p>
               <p>What is the difference betwixt the Jew outwardly,<note place="margin">35. <hi>Qu.</hi>
                  </note> and the Jew inwardly, and how ſhall we know the one from the other?</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou ſayſt, the Jew outwardly deſires to make a faire ſhew in the fleſh,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> or externall man, with his outward Circumciſion or Reformation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12.13. in voluntary worſhip, and not ſparing the body, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. he obſerves the leſſer Commands, &amp; leaves the greater undone, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. &amp; in one poynt he goes beyond, as thou ſayſt, he payes Tithes exactly; he makes clean the outſide of the Cup and Platter,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> and makes all foul within, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.15, 26. &amp;c. and ſo here is enough to manifeſt that thou art the man; for here thou haſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read thy ſelfe, and out of thy own mouth ſhalt thou be judged, without contending or reviling, as thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeſt us; for thou haſt been ſtriving all along hitherto, to ſet out thy ſelfe, and make a faire out-ſide, like a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, though the hypocriſie of thy heart thou couldeſt not thereby hide from the light; and who are more ſtrict in voluntary worſhip? but you can pamper your bodies, which ſhowes your zeal is not ſo hot; and inſtead of obſerving the leſſer Commands, and leaving the greater undone: you leave all undone that will not ſtand for Selfe; and preach up, and uphold theſe things for Commands, for which you have no Scripture, and ſo preach for Doctrine the Commandements of man,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9.</note> as the outward Jew did; but if one aske you for your proof for theſe things, thou ſayſt, it ſufficeth you, that there is no Command to the contrary; yea for thy ſelfe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115488:34"/>covetous ends thou art not aſhamed to fetch up old Commands, (that were fulfilled, and ſo ended) for a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for thy deceipt; as here alſo thou wouldſt ſeem to do in accuſing us for not paying Tithes exactly, as the Phariſee did, which I know is the great grief of thee, and thy Brethren, becauſe we put not into your mouths;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.5.</note> and therefore ye even prepare Warre againſt us, but when the Phariſee ſaid he payd Tithes, they was then due; for the Prieſthood to which Tithes belonged, was not yet fulfilled, and therefore not changed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was his duty ſo to do; but you Prieſts have ſo blinded the Phariſees, and profeſſors of theſe times, that they are ſo exact in paying you Tithes, and putting into your mouthes, becauſe you daub them up,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.28.</note> crying peace to them, though they have no Command from God for it; and you take it as exactly, but you have but few ſuch that you dare truſt without a Law; for (as thou ſayſt) the greateſt part of them are earthly minded, (like their Teachers,) and how haſt thou been cleanſing thy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the Cup, as if thou waſt unblameable in this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward righteouſneſs, and ſo holy in thine own eyes, that in words thou profeſſeſt perfection, and as if thou kneweſt the higheſt eſtate of Chriſtianity, and waſt in the pure Religion without ſpots, &amp; guided by Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, uſualy ſpeaking by the motion of the Holy Ghoſt, but even condemned thy Brethren, and wouldſt not anſwer for them; but ſaid, thou was none of theſe Hirelings, nor greedy Doggs, &amp;c. but yet could not keep thy tongue for uttering forth the foulneſs of thy heart, which hath overwhelmed thee all along, and out of thy own mouth haſt been proved a lyer; and thus thou art plainly dealt with, and judged out of thy own mouth; and the Scriptures aforeſaid, which thou haſt quoted, ſhall ſtand and witneſs againſt thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115488:35"/>
But the Jew inwardly thou ſayſt, truſts in the Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> and hath no confidence in the fleſh; but this thou doſt not, for then thou would'ſt truſt him for thy main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not ſtand in need of the arm of fleſh, upon which thou relyeſt: neither doſt thou firſt make clean the inſide of the Cup, that the outſide may be fair alſo, as thou ſayſt, the inward Jew doth; but though thou haſt been much labouring with feigned words of thy own wiſdom, and ſelfe-juſtification, to deck and adorn the outſide, painting it with Scripture-words and expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet thy inſide is ſo foul, that it defiles the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide alſo, ſo that it makes thee odious to all but the blinde; and manifeſts thy heart to be yet uncircumciſed from ſin, and a ſtranger to the inward Croſſe, by which thou art not crucified to the world, nor the world to thee; for then it would not ſuffice thee to take the tenth part of the increaſe of the labour of the Labourers, by the will of man, without any Command from God, as thou doſt, living at eaſe like a Droan upon the ſame, and therefore thy heart is far off uprightneſs: all which the Jew inwardly, thou ſayſt doth witneſs; and thus in a word, thou ſeeſt there is as much difference betwixt the one and the other, as betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and an executor of Chriſts Doctrine and way; and thus in a word, thou haſt marked out thy ſelfe, and art found out of the way and Doctrine of Chriſt, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, deſpiſing, and gain, ſaying thoſe that abide in it; and thus by thy fruits art thou known, as thou ſayſt, the one may be known from the other; And thus proud <hi>Goliah,</hi> thy head is cut off with thy own ſword.</p>
               <p>Whether they that profeſs themſelves the Miniſters of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 36.</note> and cannot give account of their Miniſtry and faith, but acts contrary to the Scripture, the Doctrine and practiſe of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and teacheth people ſo, be not ſuch as abides not in the Doctrine of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115488:35"/>Chriſt, but brings another Doctrine, and ſo are the Witches, Magicians, and deceivers, Antichriſts and falſe Teachers, who are not to be received, but deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>And in thy Anſwer thou confeſſeſt,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> that they which are truly ſuch in Doctrine and life, as this Query deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes, may be truly termed ſpirituall Witches and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, and muſt be rejected as falſe Teachers, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts.</p>
               <p>Here thou haſt paſſed the ſentence unto thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation;<note place="margin">Reply,</note> for thou art the man, as ſufficiently is proved, both out of thy own mouth, and the Scriptures, which thou thy ſelfe haſt quoted as aforeſaid; and ſo henceforward, let all people take notice, that thou <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Draton</hi> of King <hi>Rippon</hi> in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> art a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Witch and Magician; and they are to reject thee, as a falſe Teacher and an Antichriſt, as here out of thy own mouth is plainly proved; and this, him thou call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>James Parnell,</hi> doth teſtifie, and deny thee with thy Sorcery, Ribbonds, Stones, Waters, Glaſſes, Powders, Charms, and other like Enchantments, which thou, who art given up to believe lies, impudently would caſt upon him, and thoſe thou calleſt his confederacy, who abhorrs all ſuch abhomination, and therefore returns it into thy own boſom, from whence it comes.</p>
               <p>And thus thou ſayſt by clear Scripture and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note place="margin">Prieſt.</note> thou haſt anſwered the bold Queries, of him who is known to the World, to be out a boy, or ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>As thou beganneſt with a lie in thy mouth,<note place="margin">Reply.</note> ſo alſo thou endeſt with a lie; for by plain Scripture, and true experience, thou haſt not anſwered theſe Queries; for in many things thou mayſt finde no Scripture at all in the leaſt to countenance thee, then thou pleadeſt old ſtories and Records, and ſaith alſo, it ſufficeth thee, that there is no Scripture to the contrary; but thou ſhalt know, that in any thing that thou doſt, in which the Scripture
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115488:36"/>will not ſtand for thee, it will in the ſame ſtand againſt thee; and alſo when thou didſt wreſt any Scripture for thy own ends, it was made uſe of to witneſs againſt thee in the ſame; and how haſt thou anſwered by thy own experience, when as thou ſtole the Apoſtles De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and ſet it down, even word for word, to prove the eſtate of a Chriſtian, when as it was proved out of thy own mouth, that thou art not come to witneſs in poſſeſſion, the loweſt eſtate of a Chriſtian; and thus thou might have been aſhamed to boaſt of thy Age, who art found ſuch an impudent lyer, as to ſay by clear Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and experience, thou anſwered theſe. Queries, (which are not ſo bold as true,) in which all that are not wilfully blinde, will witneſs againſt thee; and thus him thou contemneſt, as a boy or ſtripling, is made able to cut off thy head with thy own ſword; and therefore henceforward, let ſhame and confuſion of face cover thee, for boaſting of thy age, who yet knoweſt not, That the wiſdom and power of the Almighty, ſtands not in the number of years, or the arm of fleſh; but the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous are as bold as a Lion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.1.</p>
               <p>And now to thy Counter-Queries, as thou calleſt hem, which for a Compeiment, thou biddeſt me give hee leave to propound, but meaned not to ſtay to know whether I did ſo or nay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115488:36"/>
               <head>Firſt concerning honour and reſpect to be given to men.</head>
               <p>And to the ſubſtance of theſe Querie, I anſwer, that Chriſt himſelfe cries down all earthly honour and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and reſpect of mans Perſon, and onely attole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the honour that is of God, and cometh from God and belongs unto the ſeed of God which is not known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you Children of this world, whoſe honour and glory is of this world, in whom the ſeed of the Serpent rules head, to which no worſhip not honour is due, the which all the world wonders after &amp; worſhip the beaſt &amp; his image, but none of theſe Scriptures which thou haſt quoted, doth at all maintaine, your heatheniſh breeding, worſhip, honour, manners and reſpect as you call it, but now he is riſen and reignes to whom all Nations muſt bow, to whom alone, belongs all honour, praiſe, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and thanks: therefore ſilence proud fleſh that would goe about to rob him, its you that are offended in him, and perſecute him becauſe he cannot bow unto you, and as for that Scripture, Honour all men, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer with another Scripture which thou haſt quoted, <hi>Pſl.</hi> 15.4. in whoſe eies a vile perſon is contemned: here all men are not honoured but in the Lord, therefore you that abide not in the doctrine of Chriſt, muſt not be received nor bidden Gods ſpeed: And as for that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.22. which thou quoteſt in thy ſeventh Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I anſwer with <hi>Solomons</hi> words, wiſdom is the gray haire, and an undefiled life is old age:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 4.8.9.</note> and this is not without honour, though by the world condemned.</p>
               <p>And to thy 9 Query, whether ſtanding bare,<note place="margin">9 <hi>Query.</hi>
                  </note> with the head uncovered, before the Magiſtrates be not a decent poſture, ſence it is a poſture that the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in the behalfe of God; which to prove thou quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4.5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, no man muſt be honoured in reſpect to his perſon,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> and the honour of juſtice and equity lyeth not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115488:37"/>in the putting off the hate, or keeping it on, but it is a heatheniſh cuſtome, contrary to any Scripture rule or example, and therefore not a decent but an unſeemly poſture, (as thou calleſt it) for men ſo to adore one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers perſons: and that Magiſtrate that ſeeks for, or owns ſuch a thing, ſtandes in his own will and is partiall, and rules not for God, but for himſelfe, and ſuch God doth not ſtile as Gods upon earth, (as thou ſay'ſt) but rather unjuſt ſtewards: and thou blind guide read in the 3 verſe of the Chapter aforeſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2</note> and ſee what is the head of the man: but thy head is the Serpent, and according to thy own meaning moſt of ye Prieſts condemnes your ſelves in this, who commonly have your heads covered with Caps, when you pretend to pray or propheſy.</p>
               <p>And that Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11. which thou haſt quoted in thy 10. Querie, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. which thou haſt quoted in thy 11. Querie, was not ſpoken to the world, who accounts man in gay clothing, and a Gold Ring as a ſuperior, and a man in vile and poore ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as an inferior, and accordingly prefers them &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects them, contrary to Scripture, and you leaders cauſe them to erre, therefore wreſt not the Scripture, for your own ends, leſt in turn to your deſtruction 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p>Whether the pronounce of the ſecond perſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Q.</hi> 12.</note> ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, may not out of the Hebrew and Greek be as well ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>you</hi> as <hi>thou,</hi> eſpecially ſince in the plurall number, it is alwayes rendered ye &amp; not thee, &amp; the Dutch tongue, whence we borrow much of our language hath (you.)</p>
               <p>Here thou ſonne of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> who art thy carnall reaſon in thy languages confuſed, who ſtumbleſt at the plaine language (thou:) what is that in thee that cannot beare the word <hi>thou,</hi> which is the ſingle proper lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to a ſingle perſon, as well as you, which thou confeſſeſt is a borrowed language: &amp; thus the Hebrews &amp; the Grecians &amp; the Romans &amp; the Dutch will condemn you, who are content with their naturall language.</p>
               <p>Whether it hath not beene ever accounted rude<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Q.</hi> 13.</note>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115488:37"/>and Ruſticall in this Nation for inferior men to ſpeake unto others their ſuperiors by the word (thou) and not you, and alſo to ſtand with their hats on, unleſſe leave were given them ſo to do.</p>
               <p>Thou blind ſot, thou haſt laide thy ſelfe naked to the world (with thy rude and ruſticall Querie) it was never accounted ſo, but by <hi>Dives</hi>-nature which is ſwelled with Pride and arrogancy, yea that which would be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove God, which muſt come downe into the pit: Is not God the ſuperior of all, then why do you give unto him that rude and ruſticall language, (as thou calleſt it): here thou manifeſts thy ſelfe amongſt the Heathen, who know not God, who excerciſe Lordſhip and authority one of another, and ſo you rule in your own wills,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25.</note> and would not ſuffer your fellow creatures to put their hats on their heads, but as you give them leave, and ſo are out of the doctrine of Chriſt, with your rude and ruſticall Spirits; And was not (thou) the language betwixt God and <hi>Adam,</hi> and betwixt God and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſo all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Scripture to one particular perſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.11.12. <hi>Exod.</hi> 10 11.12.</note> then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or nay is thine a ruſticall proud Spirit, that canſt not receive the language thou giveſt unto God: and thus thou haſt ſufficiently fomed out thy ſhame: and I am ſure now thou ſpeakeſt not by the motion of the Holy-Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Whether ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles taught us to alter or violate the civill ſpeeches and cuſtoms of the Nation where we live,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 14</note> by which our reverence to others is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and accordingly expected, if not commanded alſo and thou quoteſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is not your teacher, for out of his doctrine ye are found, in the pride of your hearts,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> contemning his ſpeech and language, and are not contented with your naturall language, but borrowes of others, in which cuſtome we are not to follow you, out of the language of the Scripture, and ſo here by thy Querie, you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe no reverence of God, becauſe to him you uſe the word <hi>Thou,</hi> which you do account an uncivill ſpeech
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115488:38"/>therefore now ſee what is that which takes offence, at that which God accepts; it muſt needs be of proud Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and that ſame took offence at the Apoſtle, who ſaid Give no offenre, yet the truth is a ſtumbling ſtone, and a Rock of offence, therefore now ſee how thou ſtumbleſt at the noon day: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <head>Thy next is concerning Salutations at your meetings with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or departings from others.</head>
               <p>Unto which I anſwer, that your heatheniſh cuſtoms traditions and ſalutations I do deny, and know them to be contrary to Scripture: for, ſaith it, let him that nameth the name of God depart from iniquity; therefore you that are in iniquity do take his name in vaine, and make a cuſtom and by-word of it, amongſt your ſelves when you meet with or depart from one another, and ſo your Children learne it at you, and by imitation uſe his name before they do know whether there be a God or nay.</p>
               <p>And to that in <hi>Ruth</hi> 2.4. and to that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1 29.8. which thou haſt quoted in thy 15. and 16. Qu. I anſwer, They that there named the name of the Lord knew him and that in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> will witneſſe againſt you, that you have nothing to do to name his name, nor to have ſuch words ſpoken to you, who know him not: and read what God ſaith to the wicked, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. and why call ye me Lord and do not the things which I ſay: but the ſalutations of the Saints I own, who are not by cuſtom lead; <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.46.</p>
               <p>And to <hi>Math.</hi> 10.12. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.5. which here thou haſt quoted, I anſwer that you are no Miniſters nor Meſſengers of Chriſt, who are found out of his doctrine, therefore peace is not given you to ſpeake, but as falſe Prophets you ſpeak it to that which is for death, becauſe that puts into your mouthes; and even prepares war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that do witneſſe the Son of peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115488:38"/>
               <head>Thy next is concerning meate, drinke, and apparel.</head>
               <p>And to thy firſt Query of that, I anſwer, All the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God are good in their places, and all things for the uſe of man who dwells in the moderation, but curſed to you, who live under the curſe, in the luſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom the creation grones, who know not the pure wiſdom, that made all things,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</note> to teach you how to uſe all things, to the glory of God, and therefore are out of the right: and thy 23.24. Qu. are here anſwered, but you are they whoſe Kingdom ſtands in meats and drinks and apparel, who are taking thought what to eat, what to drink, and where withall to be clothed, <hi>math.</hi> 6, 15.</p>
               <p>And to this Querie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 22.</note> where hath God enjoyned men to drink water, in any part of his word.</p>
               <p>I anſwer thou may'ſt be aſhamed to boaſt of thy age, who askeſt ſuch a childiſh Querie: I might as well ask thee, where God injoyned men to drink beare, for water is the originall of all drinks, for in the daies of old, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was the common drink; haſt thou not read of <hi>Jacobs</hi> well, where Chriſt drunk, then who art thou that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeſt water, it is a ſigne thou ſerveſt the luſt, but if any drink water who know the goodneſſe of it, what is that to thee? who injoynes thee to drink water?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <head>And in thy <hi>25.</hi> Querie, thou anſwerest thy ſelfe.</head>
               <p>And this Querie is, Whether one may not ſatisfy the fleſh even in over faſting and overwatching the body which to prove thou quoteſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But I perceive thou wilt have a care of that, who haſt been pleading ſo much for the body which is the moſt thou mindeſt; thy zeale is not ſo hot: but they that dwell in the power of God are free from this, and yet know how to keepe under the body and not ſatisfying
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115488:39"/>the laſt, but you that know not the Creator, truſt in the Creature.</p>
               <p>And here thou askeſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 27.</note> whether are not the Saints to ſanctifie their meats and drinks, by Prayer and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, before and after they eat and drink, which to prove, thou quoteſt 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.16.</p>
               <p>To the pure all thingsare pure,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> but thy prayers are abomination, who art in the luſt; but which of theſe Scriptures maintains your Cuſtom after meat;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note> but the Saints receives nothing of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.2</note> but with Thanksgiving, and glory to God, but your bleſſings are curſed, and here is thy 28. Query anſwered alſo.</p>
               <p>Whether the Apoſtles Interdiction be abſolute againſt all Ornaments,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 29.</note> or Comparative onely; and thou haſt quoted a Scripture in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. which anſwereth thee: where thou mayſt read, what Ornaments he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of, and here thy 30.31.32. Query is anſwered; but moderation in every thing I own, but what is waſt is for the luſt, both in Kings, Princes, and great perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, (as thou calleſt them) but with us there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, neither taking thought, what to eat, what to drink, or wherewithall to be cloathed, as the Children of this world do, amongſt whom thou art found; but our Kingdom is not of this world: and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell</hi> after the fleſh was a figure of <hi>Iſraell</hi> after the ſpirit: therefore now read their adorning if thou canſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no Creature was made for the luſt, though luſtfull men abuſe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115488:39"/>
               <head>Thy next is concerning Pride.</head>
               <p>And thy firſt Queſtion of this is, whether pride doth lie in Apparel (though there may be much waſtfulneſs, vanity, and oſtentation committed therein) or inwardly, in the heart and minde of the poor, as well as of the rich, and thou quoteſt <hi>Mark</hi> 7.21.22, 23.</p>
               <p>The Scripture which thou haſt quoted,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> doth anſwer thy Queſtion, where pride lieth; but Apparel is a dead thing, and no pride in it, but the vanity and waſtfulneſs (which thou confeſſeſt is committed therein) figures forth the pride of the heart; and where riches is, this is ſhowne: (therefore you Prieſts, look at home, and judge your ſelves) though poor and rich be both in one nature before the Regeneration, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2, 3.</p>
               <p>Whether one of the greateſt things, that puffs up the hearts of men, be not knowledge?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 34.</note> whether it be true or falſe, and imagined only: and thou quoteſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1, 2.</p>
               <p>You that are carnall, and fleſhly,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> are puffed up with your fleſhly notionall knowledge; and in that yo uſteal from others experiences; but the true knowledge of the ſpirit puffs not up, but judges down that which would be exalted; but this unto thee, is a myſtery, becauſe thy knowledge hath blinded thy eye, who art confuſed in thine Imaginations; ſo read thy ſelfe in the Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, which thou haſt quoted.</p>
               <p>Whether another thing that exalts a man in pride,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 35.</note> and makes him deſpiſe his Brethren (and perhaps, thoſe that are better then himſelf) be not a Conceited &amp; ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen holineſs, ſeeing ſuch a proud Saint is brought in <hi>Iſay</hi> 65.5. which thing alſo (thou ſayſt) is verified in the Phariſee and the Publican, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115488:40"/>
Thou haſt here anſwered thy ſelfe, with theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wherein thou mayſt read thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> who thinkeſt thy ſelfe more holy then thy Brethren, and would only anſwer for thy ſelfe, and not for thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, though thou art found in the ſame practices; but thou blinde Phariſee, he was not a Saint, which was ſpoken of in <hi>Iſay</hi> 65.5. but he was a Saint, which ſaid, We are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickedneſs, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.19. and here alſo thy 36. Queſtion is anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the Scripture which thou haſt quoted, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. who art a falſe Teacher, doting about Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>And here thou askeſt whether a young man be not the proneſt of all other,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 31.</note> to be thus ſeduced and puffed up: and thou quoteſt 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p>Thy ſpite is much againſt youth; but him thou ſhootes at,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> thou canſt not hit, becauſe thou art blinde, and canſt not divide the word aright; but thou mayſt plainly have readthy ſelfe in that Chapter aforeſaid, and finde that thou art the novice who knowes not the truth, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeſt the young man, becauſe of his youth, which is contrary to <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <head>And thy next is, to maintain Swearing.</head>
               <p>And thy firſt Query of this is, whether it be lawfull now,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 31.</note> in the new Teſtament to take an Oath before lawful Authority, to put an end to controverſies, and thou quoteſt <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p>This which thou goeſt about now to uphold manifeſts thee an enemy to Chriſt and his Doctrine,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> who ſaith, Swear not at all; for ſaith he, it hath been ſaid in the old time, thou ſhalt not forſweare thy ſelfe, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine Oath; but I ſay unto you, Swear not at all, but let your yea be yea, and your nay be
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115488:40"/>nay; for what is more is evill: now here he doth not only forbid falſe ſwearing, but alſo all ſwearing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.33.34. &amp;c. and alſo the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> doth the ſame, in <hi>James</hi> 5.12. both which Scriptures thou haſt quoted in thy 39. Query, and ſo here out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, again thou art found in the evill; and all you that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe one another without ſwearing, and ſo are more then yea and nay; and what is more is evill, (ſaith Chriſt:) now read your condemnation, and as for that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. there the Apoſtle was ſpeaking by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, how the Lord made a Covenant, and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with an oath, which is Chriſt Jeſus the everlaſting Oath, who ſaith, ſwear not at all: and the Apoſtle brought a compariſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from men in ſtrife and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; but this doth not at all maintain ſwearing now; for ſtrife and controverſie is out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and ſuch runs into the ſwearing, and into the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, amongſt whom thou art found upholding the evill and oppoſing Chriſts Doctrine, and ſo art found in the condemnation of the Devil, <hi>James</hi> 5.12. this was not the Saints practiſe; for in the new Covenant, neither ſtrife nor ſwearer is; and thus you leaders cauſe men to erre, by upholding that which Chriſt is againſt, &amp; here thy 39. Query is anſwered.</p>
               <p>Here thou askeſt whether <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf did not ſwear,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 40.</note> in theſe words, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. as the truth of Chriſt is in me, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Oh thou enemy of truth, that would heare ſcandall, and accuſe <hi>Paul</hi> for ſwearing, that ſo thou might uphold ſwearing: but by what doth he here ſwear? this is plain Language.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115488:41"/>
               <head>And thy next is concerning outward materiall Churches, and the publick exerciſes therein.</head>
               <p>Moſt of theſe Queries are anſwered in my Reply to thy Anſwer to my 17th Query,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> wherein I have declared why I object againſt your Steeple-houſes, which thou calleſt Churches.</p>
               <p>Here thou askeſt if ſuch meetings may not be mixt Aſſemblies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 44.</note> of learned, &amp; unlearned, of believers and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, and thou quotes 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23.</p>
               <p>But the un-believers are not owned by the believers,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> though he come amongſt the believers, as in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. 15, 16, 17, 18. then the Miniſters are far off, being main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by unbelievers, as thou art; for though thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeſt the greateſt part are earthly minded, and worldly minded: thou yet art maintained by them, and I am ſure, they that come into the true faith, which purifieth the heart, come out from amongſt you, ſo that you are not much mixed; for you are all one nature, like Prieſt, like people.</p>
               <p>And in thy 47. &amp; 48. Query, thou askeſt, if Chriſt and his Apoſtles, did not frequent the Synagogues.</p>
               <p>Yea they did,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and ſo do we your Idoll-Temples; but therein the Jews will condemn you, who ſuffered them to ſpeak, as in that Scripture which thou haſt quoted in <hi>Acts</hi> 13, 14, 15. which ſhall ſtand and witneſs againſt you, who will not ſuffer us to ſpeak in your Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, but ſuffers your flocks to hale us forth, and fall upon us like Wolves, and your Magiſtrates to hale us to priſon; therefore read your condemnation, you perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters, and thy 49. Query is anſwered already with the other aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Here thou askeſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 50.</note> if the Prophet did not complain to God, againſt the profaners, and deſtroyers of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115488:41"/>
This Scripture which thou haſt quoted, doth anſwer thee, but it doth not uphold your Idolls Temples,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> who worſhip you know not what, wherein you teach for Doctrine the traditions of men, and there are found in the ſteps of the Phariſees, offering up your abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Chriſt marked you out in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5. where he meant as he ſpoke; and all you do there, is for ſelfe, and not for God; for he ſaith, in vain do you worſhip him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.7, 8, 9. and here thy 51. Query is anſwered, but take notice, your Steeple-houſes are not the houſes of God, as before is proved.</p>
               <p>Is it unlawful to call, either Baptiſme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 52.</note> or the Supper of the Lord, a Sacrament or obliging Myſtery? ſince that name imports no more, and you cannot deny, but that both theſe are myſtical things, and obliging myſteries, to the waſhing away of ſin, and the following of Chriſt into his life &amp; death. Is thy Baptiſme now become an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Myſtery to the waſhing away of ſin,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> which in thy Anſwer to my 21. Query, thou ſaid, was not abſolutely neceſſary, but lawfull onely? can it waſh away ſin, and yet not be neceſſary; but this is all thou knoweſt of that myſtery that waſheth away ſin, or deire after it; for where ſin is waſhed away, this confuſion ſtayes not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde.</p>
               <p>Yea I do deny that there is any thing in your ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Infants, or your Bread and Wine (which doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit) as is manifeſt by theſe that receive them of you, who never yet was waſhed from their ſins and pollutions, or ever taſted of the death of the Croſſe;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</note> but the Baptiſme I own, and the Supper of the Lord I owne; but the word Sacrament I deny, for the which you have no Scripture, whatſoever thou ſayſt it doth import.</p>
               <p>And thy 53.54. &amp; 55. Queries are anſwered in my Reply to thy Anſwer, to my 21. Query, and thy 56. and 57. Queries are anſwered in my Reply to thy Anſwer, to my 25. Query.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115488:42"/>
Who is there among you who are called Quakers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 58.</note> or the other Sectarians your fore-fathers, that hath rightly declared the myſtery of Chriſts body and blood in your diſſentings from us? ſince none of you have declared this according to our Lords intent, <hi>John</hi> 6.33.</p>
               <p>As for Sectarians (as thou calleſt them) they are in your Generation:<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> and art not thou aſhamed to call them our fore-fathers, when as they now joyn with you againſt us, yea and in this very thing, wherein they are blinde as you are; but the myſtery we know, and have declared to the comfort of many a reſtleſs ſoul, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could finde true comfort in your dark and dead forms, as thouſands in the Nation will witneſs; and this we have declared according to our Lords intent: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou lier and ſlanderer, ſtop thy mouth, and take not his name in vain, and that Scripture in <hi>John</hi> 6.33. which thou haſt quoted, will witneſs againſt thee, in that thou wouldeſt uphold: and thy 59. Query is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with thy 56. &amp; 57.</p>
               <p>And thy next is concerning the preſent Miniſters and Teachers, and their maintenance.</p>
               <p>Were there no Miniſters in this Nation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 60.</note> that held forth the truth amongſt us, till you and your aſſociates roſe up? ſince we have our Lords promiſe, the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church, and, be hold I am with you to the end of the world.</p>
               <p>What is become then of all your fore-fathers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 61.</note> theirs and ours, who died ſince the Apoſtles dayes, till your ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up with a pretended ſpirit?</p>
               <p>Thou carnall one,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> haſt thou nothing to do, but to raiſe the dead, to diſpute about? but, to anſwer a fool, I ſay they are gone, as the juſt and righteous Judge hath
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115488:42"/>diſpoſed; but now he calles all every where to repent, his Trumpets are ſounding a warning, and there was none that preached for hire, that held forth the truth in the life and power of it, but made a Trade and gain of the Letter, from it ſpeaking a divination of their own brain, as you do now, and thoſe was your fore-fathers; but if you had the Lords promiſe, that the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt you; for the Lord will be with you; then what need you a Law of man to ſet you up, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold you, and maintain you: therefore it follows, the Lord is againſt you and his promiſes doth not belong unto you, who dare not truſt him; and therefore are but pretenders, and this the ſpirit of truth in us can tell you.</p>
               <p>If there were ſome taught of God before you were called,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 62.</note> why are they not owned by any of you?</p>
               <p>Thou art not one that art ſo taught; for thou art found out of his Doctrine, therefore with that ſtop thy mouth, and do not bely us: for who receive and obey the truth, we do own, whatſoever they have been, and here alſo thy 63<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 64. Query is anſwered.</p>
               <p>And thy 65.66. &amp; 67. Queries are anſwered in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to thy Anſwer to my 9. &amp; 10th Query.<note place="margin">Anſ.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Is the teaching Prieſthood to ceaſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 68.</note> till the ſpirituall Melchizedeck come unto us, to bleſſe us after the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all our enemies, with the heavenly bread and wire, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.18.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. that you ſay the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Aaron</hi> with the Law annexed of Tithes, is ceaſed under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Yea, ſo it is ceaſed: and thoſe Scriptures doth not prove to the contrary but that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. doth affirm it,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> before proved; but in that you uphold it, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Tithes, you deny the ſpiritual Melehizedeck; and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115488:43"/>if that be the teaching Prieſthood, which thou meaneſt, it is already ceaſed, to many who are come to ſee the end of it; but the gift blinde your eyes, and therefore you ſtill uphold it, and lead the blindes into the ditch, and ſo the woe is to you, and not the bleſſing; and this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. &amp;c. doth not at all maintain you, and here alſo thy 69. Query is anſwered.</p>
               <p>And thy 70.71.72, &amp; 73. Queries are anſwered in my Reply to thy Anſwer to my 14th Query.</p>
               <p>Did ever the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> caſt greater reproaches upon the Proteſtant Miniſters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 74.</note> then you do; and are you not Jeſuited by ſome of her Emiſſeries, that you would have them all one with another, rooted out at once; yea can the Devil himſelf deſire more in this kinde?</p>
               <p>I ſee no difference in the ground betwixt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and you;<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> for they are bloody perſecuters, and upheld by a perſecuting Law, and ſo are you (who call your ſelves Proteſtants) and therefore no reproaches, to call you perſecuters, hirelings, falſe Teachers, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Doggs, as the Prophets of old called your fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in whoſe ſteps you are found, as is before proved; but howſoever, thou with thy lying ſpirit termeſt us of the Jeſuites, both thou and thy Brethren have in this been ſufficiently proved lyars: therefore by the ſword of the Lord you muſt all be rooted out, yea ye muſt all fall together,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.91.10, 11.</note> he will make a grievous ſlaughter, from the leaſt to the greateſt; for his hand is ſtretched out againſt you; and therefore your Father the Devil beſtirs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe amongſt you, to ſtand up for his Kingdom; and where did ever the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> perſecute any, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life, more then you do: therefore let guilt ſtrike you, and put not the Devil ſo far from you, when as he fights for you;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or. 10.4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> but carnall Weapons we ſhall not uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, to root you out, but our Weapons are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115488:43"/>and mighty through God to the pulling down of ſtrong holdes: therefore tremble all ye enemies of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <head>Thy next is concerning the Inward light.</head>
               <p>Is there not a falſe light as well as a true light,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 75.</note> &amp; thou quotes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14. Thou haſt anſwered thy ſelfe with this Scripture, and I have already proved that this falſe light rules in thee, as an Angel of light, who art a Miniſter of Antichriſt, transforming thy ſelfe as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt, but out of their life and practice art found, and therefore guided by a falſe light, which is an evill eye, and dangerous darkneſſe, ſo that thou canſt accuſe others, but canſt not ſee the falſeneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of thine own heart, but thinks that thou ſpeakeſt by the motion of the Holy-Ghoſt, when as therein thou haſt ſufficiently beene proved a lier, and thus Satan rules in thee, and makes thee beleive he is God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. and here is thy 76, Querie anſwered alſo, and that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which thou quoteſt in <hi>Math.</hi> 6.23. ſhall ſtand and witneſſe againſt thee.</p>
               <p>Are we not therefore, to try mens pretended light by the law and word of God, and thou quoteſt <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20.</p>
               <p>You neither know the law nor word or God,<note place="margin">P. Anſ.</note> and therefore relyes upon the law and word of man, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the law &amp; word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; yet pretendeſt to the light &amp; the law and the word of God and ſo by it art tryed, and found to be a deceiver who puts the letter for the word and the letter for the law, both which is within: but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy own meaning, thou art out of the light, who atteſt many things contrary to the law and teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as before is proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115488:44"/>
What may men think of your pretended light, who hate ſo many of your brethren in the Miniſtery of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 78.</note> and thou quoteſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p>The thoughts of man is vaine,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> and would'ſt thou have the light tryed by that? here thou erres from the law, and from the teſtimony, and ſo confirmes my former anſwer: therefore ceaſe thy falſe accuſing, from the evill thoughts of thy heart, for none of my brethren in the Miniſtery of God do I hate: but I deny that thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are mine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35.</note> for you are ſpring of another ſeed, and ſo are become another generation, in which the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood is found ſhed, and therefore murderers; unto whom belongs this in 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.9. and Chap. 3.15. where you may read your ſelves.</p>
               <p>Is there not another light to go before the light of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 79.</note> ſeeing the wiſe men that came from the Eaſt, were guided unto Chriſt by a ſtar? <hi>Mat th.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Thy ignorance of Chriſt and his light,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> thou haſt here manifeſted, and ſo confirmed my reply to thy anſwer to my 30. Querie, that thou would'ſt not have confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Chriſt doth enlighten every one that cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, had not <hi>John</hi> ſo plainly affirmed it in, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. and that thou never yet ſaw his ſtar, who thinks that it is not his light: therefore thou that would'ſt ſet up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother light before the light of Chriſt, art a deceiver and a bringer in of falſe lights.</p>
               <p>Is not the ſure propheticall Word,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 86.</note> a light that ſhines in a dark corner, till the true day light ariſe, in your hearts? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
               <p>But it is the light of Chriſt, that leads unto Chriſt the perfect day?<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> which light ſhines in darkneſſe, and darkneſſe comprehends it not, and therefore thou looks without,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5.</note> for another light before the light of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Whether the life of Chriſt be not the true light that men are to waite for,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 8 1.</note> and wherein the true Children of light are to walk? and thou quoteſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.4. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5, 9.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt here anſwered thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> for his life is the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115488:44"/>light of men, which they muſt waite to know within them, to guide them: and thou that would'ſt ſet up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother light, before this light, art a deceiver; and this is the light which now is come into the world, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying againſt the world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.19.20.</note> and manifeſting you to be the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ers of the world, who have long ſet up falſe lights to draw from this true light, the minds of people: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now you can no longer hide your ſelves from this true light, you ſtand up to oppoſe it where it is ſet up, and ſome calls it a naturall light, and an inſufficient light, but it is your condemnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <head>Thy next is concerning Prophets and Propheteſſes</head>
               <p>Whether ſome men may not be acted with a Spirit of falſehood,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 82.</note> and deluſion, even then when they think they Propheſie by the Spirit of God as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was, 1 <hi>King</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>This is already anſwered in my reply to thy anſwer to any 6th. Query:<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> and thou in divers places to be thus acted.</p>
               <p>Whether the Lord did ever ſend forth boyes or ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to be his prophets &amp; publike teachers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Q.</hi> 83.</note> ſeeing <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt who was born to be a Prophet, of the moſt high, and was filled with the Holy-Ghoſt from his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, was not ſent forth to preach and Propheſie till he was 30 yeares old <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p>How often have I made thy folly and ignorance,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> in this to appeare? and that thou might be aſhamed to boaſt of thy age, who ſo often haſt erred not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures nor the power of God, who would limit it to time &amp; age, in which I have before ſufficiently anſwered thee and now I ſay the Lord ſent forth <hi>Ieremiah</hi> when he was but a Child,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.6.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.</note> and out of the mouths of Babes and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the Lord hath perfected his praiſe, therefore hence-forward ſtop thy mouth, for deſpiſing any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becauſe of their youth, but know this that whomſoever
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115488:45"/>God calls to his Miniſtry, he by his power and wiſdom doth fit them, for the ſame, and contrary to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man, doth the Lord work, therefore if thou waſt not blind, thou would'ſt not ſo much looke at the creature,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 11.25.</note> but at the power of God in the creature: but as it is written, He hath hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed them unto Babes: and here thy 84. Querie, is alſo anſwered.</p>
               <p>Whether the Lord will breake his own orders and commands,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 85</note> expreſſely ſet down in his word, where he ſaith (as you already heard) by <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p>And unto this I have already anſwered,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> at to thy 37, Querie: therefore thou blaſphemer, ſtop thy mouth and be aſhamed thus to accuſe the Lord, becauſe he is pleaſed to make his power known, in babes and youth, for <hi>Timothy,</hi> to whom <hi>Paul</hi> writes this Epiſtle was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but a youth, as <hi>Paul</hi> writes 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.11.12. and there read thy rebuke,</p>
               <p>Where did Chriſt or his Apoſtles ſend forth women to be publique propheteſſes as you have don many and ſome of them not long ſince infamous for lewdneſſe of life.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 86.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Oh thou impudent one,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> how doſt thou provoke the Lord to indignation againſt thee, that darſt lay any ſuch thing to the Charge of Gods elect? oh thou lier, whom doſt thou accuſe of lewdneſſe? we abhor thy words for all lewdneſſe, and prophaneſſe we teſtify againſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it doth appeare, or any thing contrary to the pure divine light, which now in thy conſcience, and many other conſciences doth here witneſſe, for us, againſt thee who art given up to beleivelies, and report them: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore read thy portion in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. and read an anſwer to thy Querie, in <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.28. where the Lord ſaith the ſons and Daughters ſhall propheſy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1.2.3.4.</note> and none other do we own but who immediately are caried forth by the Spirit of the Lord, without the commiſſion of man: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou falſly accuſeſt us, who ſaiſt we ſend forth any.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115488:45"/>
If you be extraordinary Prophets immediatly inſpired as many of you pretend to be,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 87.</note> where are the miracles which ſuch inſpired men wrought in times paſt?</p>
               <p>But that we are ſo inſpired thou doſt not beleive,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> (as may eaſily be diſcerned by thy Querying) and therefore unto thee no ſigne ſhall be given who art in the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous generation who cannot ſee the ſignes that follow the truth, <hi>Math.</hi> 16.4.</p>
               <p>What have you foretold by way of praediction,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 88.</note> which hath accordingly come to paſſe as the Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and inſpired men were wont to do?</p>
               <p>If thou canſt tax us to the contrary thou maiſt,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> we beare not witneſſe of our ſelves, but he that beleives hath the witneſſe within himſelf.</p>
               <p>And as for thy 89.90.91. and 92. Queries, they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in my reply to thy anſwer to my 16. Querie, and thy 93. Querie, is anſwered in my anſwer to thy Query concerning Salutations.</p>
               <p>Whether is a multitude of diſciples and followers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Que.</hi> 94.</note> ſure figne that his doctrine is from heaven, who is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, ſeeing the way is broad that leads to deſtruction and many there be that find it, and thou quoteſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.13. and 2, <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</p>
               <p>Many are called but few chofen,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and many for a time followed Chriſt, ſo that the ruler ſaid if we let this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low alone, all men will goe after him, which is the cry of you and your rulers, now againſt the meſſengers of truth, and haſt thou never read of the multitudes that followed Chriſt, but few there be that enter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.48. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.14.</note> becauſe ſtrate is the Gate; but devide England into parts, and ſee if the greateſt number belong not unto you, who are in the broad way: your lives preach you forth, therefore now thou ſhould have firſt asked thy ſelf this Query, and ſaid Is it I, and ſo have laid thy hand upon thy mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115488:46"/>
Seeing this age is earthly-minded and willing to ſerve God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 95.</note> with that which coſts them nothing contrary to the pious and noble ſpirit of <hi>David</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.24. is it any great wonder that your doctrine againſt Tithes, ſhould find ſo many willing yea greedy entertayners of it, as it hath done ſince it was firſt broached?</p>
               <p>The more is your ſhame, who are teachers in this age, that are ſo earthly-minded,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> who have ſo long taken their monies for that which is not bread, and their labour for that which profiteth not:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.2.</note> do you not herein manifeſt your ſelves to be ſuch as run, and the Lord never ſent you,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.21.22.32.</note> and therefore you profit not the people at all, but they are ſtill earthly-minded, how have you then ſowne ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things? but I ſhall prove that the earthly-minded ones ſtill ſtick unto you, for you have a law made by the will of man, ſo that if they refuſe to pay you, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake you, then by it you caſt them into priſon, and by your law take treble damage, and this they know, and therefore conſult with their earthly mindes, that it is better to pay the leſſer then the greater,<note place="margin">there is much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt ſervings God and your bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</note> though the leſſer is a greater oppreſſion: and thus mank deny the truth, though they are convinced in their conſciences thereof, therefore that which leads any from you, to take up this croſſe to own the truth, and deny you of Tithes, the ſame crucifies the earthly mind, and leade to ſuffer for conſcience. And the noble Spirit of <hi>David</hi> condemnes you: for whereas he refuſed upon gift, you will take upon gift, and if they will not give it you, you will take it by force, therefore this Scripture affords witneſſes againſt you, but hereby thou confeſſeſt, our doctrine coſts them nothing; then how ſaid'ſt thou before that <hi>James Parnels</hi> Goſpel was not without charge, and thus out of thy own mouth art thou proved a liar.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115488:46"/>
Did ever Chriſt or the Apoſtles diſturb the Prieſts, and Miniſters of theſe times,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 96.</note> while they were teaching the people, as many of you and yours have done?</p>
               <p>Both the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> declared againſt the deceivers, falſe Prophets,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.31.</note> falſe Prieſts and Hirelings, and the Apoſtles was haled out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and out of the Temple, as Chriſt told them <hi>John</hi> 16.2. as we by the ſame ſpirit do now againſt you, whom we finde in the ſame ſteps, and here thou art anſwered, if this be it thou calleſt diſturbance; but it is becauſe you would bear rule by your means, and ſuffer nothing to be publiſhed, that is againſt you, or ſtrikes at your <hi>Diana.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth the Goſpel ordinarily call any man from his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Calling,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 97.</note> whereby he ſhould maintain himſelf and his Family? and thou quoteſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7, 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28.</p>
               <p>Yea it doth, and the Scripture holds forth the ſame that they was ordinarily called from their outward Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> to preach the Goſpel to every Creature:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos.</hi> 7.14.15. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Math.</hi> 4.18.19.20.21.22.23.</note> neither doth either of theſe Scriptures which thou haſt quoted prove to the contrary; &amp; how many Scriptures didſt thou quote in thy Anſwer to my 15th Query to prove that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel might forbear working, and not to entangle themſelves with the affairs of this life: yet in all could not prove thy ſelfe a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and now thou queſtions the truth of the Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither thou nor thy Brethren was called, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture; but whomſoever the Lord calls unto his work, he doth take care both for him and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; but you that are not called by him, dare not truſt him, without a Law of man.</p>
               <p>And in thy 98. &amp; 99. Query,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.7.</note> thou ſeems to accuſe us with ſome that turned from the truth, and yielded to the deceipt of their heares, and ſo gave occaſion to ſuch as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115488:47"/>thee, who wait for occaſion to blaſpheme the truth; but it is no new thing,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 14.15.</note> but the ſame which the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares of in divers places: therefore ſaith Chriſt, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſt come, but woe unto them by whom they do come;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26 <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.5.</note> for there was then many ſuch as thee in that age who (as thou doſt) waited for occaſion to blaſpheme the truth; but if thou hadſt been then, how would'ſt thou have accuſed Chriſt, who had but twelve Apoſtles, and one of them betrayed him, and then hanged himſelfe, and another denied him: therefore let this ſtop thy mouth, for ſpeaking evil of the things thou knoweſt not; and as for <hi>Spencer</hi> and <hi>Gilpin,</hi> whom thou here nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, the truth is ſufficiently cleared of them in other Books; and the Prieſts have owned them, as they did Judas, which is the name of all that turn from the truth, after they have received it.</p>
               <p>Have ſo many fallen into diſtraction or madneſs in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sect,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu:</hi> 100.</note> or under any Doctrine, as there hath done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your hearers, eſpecially where the number of Diſciples was no more?</p>
               <p>Look at home, and anſwer thy ſelfe, witneſs your Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> as you call them; for it is the fruit of your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, who would finde out that by your wit and wiſdom, which the Lord hath hid from you; and all that you cannot ſettle in ſecurity and blindneſs, you lead them into madneſs, confuſion, and diſtraction, if they do not in time forſake you, as many will witneſs at this day that they are led by you into ſuch a Wilderneſſe, that they know not which way to get out, neither do you know how to direct them, for you are in confuſion your ſelves,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15 14.</note> and ſo the blinde leads the blinde into the ditch: therefore this might have ſtopped thy mouth from falſly accuſing us; but I remember truth was ever accounted madneſs and folly by the blinde World, who know not
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115488:47"/>that Godlineſs is great gain. And in thy 94. Query, thou waſt queſtioning the truth of our Doctrine, becauſe of the multitude of Diſciples, and now by the fewneſs; and thus thou contradicts thy ſelfe, and then after much of thy filthy ſtuffe, which all along thou haſt vented forth of thy old bottle againſt us, which upon thee I have returned again from whence it came: thou ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to accuſe our book, but doſt not ſhew wherein, and therefore I paſſe it by, as knowing thy lying ſpirit, and then thou ſtealeſt the Apoſtles words, for a Cloak for the deceipt of thy heart, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7, 8, 9. which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpoke from a true and upright heart, but thou from a falſe deceiptful heart, as all along hath been ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, and thy prayers to be abomination, and that thou haſt nothing to do to name the name of God in thy mouth, who art a worker of iniquity, and a ſtranger un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, who art found out of his Doctrine;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 19. 2 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with this Scripture I ſhall mark thee, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9.10. that all may know thee, and turn away their eares from thee, who art not to be received, but denied; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoever receives thee, or thy Doctrine, the ſame departs from the Doctrine of Chriſt; and therefore let this be a Caveat to all people, to whom it ſhall come, and look upon thee to be as <hi>Anathema, Maranatha,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>This from a friend, to all ſouls witneſſed in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences by the eternall Light of God, by which I am known and received.</hi> I. P.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
